25.000000
(sound effects complementing shot transitions)
Hey, everyone!
We're in the Silicon Valley.
First thing people normally do
when they come here
is rush to see the famous
Wozniak and Jobs garage.
That's where many years ago,
Apple was created.
But this garage behind me
is much more emblematic.
In the 1930s, it served as
the first office
for William Hewlett and David Packard,
two Stanford University graduates
who founded Hewlett-Packard,
one of the first IT giants
in America and the world.
It's believed that this is where
the modern world started.
The Silicon Valley is the place where
they create our everyday conveniences,
making billions of moneys doing it.
More and more Russian speakers
arrive here every year.
How do they end up here? What do they do?
And why in America, and not back at home?
To figure it all out, we stayed
here for almost a week
and met with a bunch
of different people.
Right. We want to make
an important note here.
The majority of this footage
was shot before the coronavirus.
But this video isn't about who's
the richest or the coolest right now.
This episode is about the value system
that allowed people to turn
an 80-kilometer stretch of land
into the technological
capital of the entire world.
This system and these values
are decades-old,
and it's very likely that even the issues
that befell the world in 2020
won't be able to change
these values too much.
Besides, the two main points
we were making in this episode
are unlikely to be affected
by the coronavirus.
The episode you're about to watch
has two main purposes.
First, to remind everyone that even if you
were born and grew up in a small town,
you can still make it
to the very top.
Second, to prove that making money
is a lot more fun than collecting it.
(exhales sharply)
Let's go!
(title card music)
(airplane sound effect)
(sound effects complementing shots)
- (Dud') You live here?
- (Davidov) Yeah. Renting.
- $10,000 a month?
- Give or take.
Well, you're at least paying
for the view as I understand.
Yeah, the house is old.
Old. But what's the average
rate here?
You won't find anything cheaper
in Los Altos Hills.
[NIKOLAY DAVIDOV]
[32 years old]
[Co-founder of Gagarin Capital venture firm.]
- Oh. So this is like a down-and-out place.
- Yeah, it's a down-and-outer.
[NIKOLAY DAVIDOV]
[32 years old]
[Co-founder of Gagarin Capital venture firm.]
Okay. What about Mountain View
where we're staying?
$6,000 minimum.
A house.
$6,000 a month.
How much do you think it's worth?
We have three bedrooms.
$2.5 to 3 million.
Three bedrooms is around that.
Dude, I could kick a hole...
I'm no Jean-Claude Van Damme,
but I could kick a hole in a wall
there just like that.
Materials cost nothing.
Labor costs a lot.
Minimum wage.
And...
meeting requirements.
No, but land probably costs a lot?
Land costs a shitton.
But labor costs the most.
For example, we recently
had another earthquake.
One of our sewage pipes
had rotted away and collapsed.
Water in the kitchen sink
stopped going away.
We called the plumbers.
They went and checked it out.
They gave us a choice of two solutions.
Worth $16,000 and $35,000.
That's local plumbing bills for you.
You should've seen their gear!
They looked like Ghostbusters.
With the backpacks
and the visors.
The snake with the camera like
the one they use for colonoscopies.
You know... It was a long pipe.
We... know what that is.
(Davidov laughs)
In plain and simple terms,
I help scale businesses.
I help businesses grow faster than
they would've without me.
I find a company
that I find promising
and start helping them out.
If they don't currently need money,
I can help in other ways.
But most of the time,
it's investment.
For example, people might need
a million dollars to finish their product
to get initial revenue
and initial user reviews.
We serve as the investor
they need.
We make a profit on helping them
then sell their now scaled up company,
and split the profit with them.
You work in an investment firm
that you founded with some partners.
You raised some money,
several millions dollars.
You find promising projects
and invest in them.
For example, you give them $100,000
in exchange for 10% of the company.
- And then your job is to make those 10% worth
$5 million instead of the initial $100,000.
- Yeah.
Exactly!
- Then you split the profit.
Is this essentially what you do?
- Yes.
(Dud') Fazliev.
(Davidov) Amazing entrepreneur
who made two good companies.
He got several offers to sell
his company in the last year.
He won't tell how much
they offered.
Can you estimate as an expert how much
his company could be worth right now?
I'm an insider.
I invested in his company too.
But it's hundreds of millions
of dollars?
Most likely.
Holy crap.
Could you explain to people
who don't deal with IT
[RUSLAN FAZLIEV]
[40 years old]
[Founded the Ecwid e-commerce platform ]
and don't read Forbes
[RUSLAN FAZLIEV]
[40 years old]
[Founded the Ecwid e-commerce platform ]
what your company does
in a few sentences?
[RUSLAN FAZLIEV]
[40 years old]
[Founded the Ecwid e-commerce platform ]
Online stores.
[RUSLAN FAZLIEV]
[40 years old]
[Founded the Ecwid e-commerce platform ]
We allow people to create online stores.
You don't pay anyone any money.
You go in and make on yourself.
For free.
- You made your first million at 21, correct?
- Yes.
How? In short.
Online stores, but they were
different online stores.
Could you hold that million
in your hands at 21?
Or was it a virtual million,
as is typical for the IT crowd?
[*He actually says he couldn't NOT hold it,]
[but it sounds like a slip of the tongue.]
At 21, I couldn't hold it*.
I remember one of my
biggest amateur mistakes.
There was a competitor company.
They were from LA, California.
They started out as consultants
on my own product, X-Cart,
[X-Cart is Fazliev's first e-commerce startup,]
[created in 2001.]
but later launched their own,
Magento.
[X-Cart is Fazliev's first e-commerce startup,]
[created in 2001.]
Right?
[X-Cart is Fazliev's first e-commerce startup,]
[created in 2001.]
Magento eventually became so big
that they sold it to eBay for $160 million.
When they sold it to eBay
for $160 million,
at that point, they were
smaller than me.
- Let me tell you, I don't have
$160 million.
- Right?
And this makes me very sad.
There were offers. But I didn't just decline.
I didn't pick up the phone.
This was a typical thing
in those years.
They'd contact tech support,
saying: "We wanna...
"We wish to talk to Ruslan."
"About what?"
"We wish to buy X-Cart."
"Oh, you don't need to talk
to Ruslan to buy X-Cart."
"You need to go to our site,
click whatever, yadda yadda."
"You don't understand.
We wish to buy X-Cart...
"the company."
But I didn't talk to them,
because I was young and stupid.
I thought they didn't understand
how this whole affair worked
and wouldn't be able to buy it.
Like, they wouldn't be dealing with
briefcases of money, you know?
(Dud') Doronichev?
(Davidov) Doronichev is great.
He's awesome.
- Was he the one who made the YouTube app?
- Yes, he made the YouTube app.
More so, Doronichev...
- Let's lock this in. A Russian guy...
- Yes.
...made the app that we use when we
can't watch YouTube on a big screen?
Yes. In fact, we use it more
than the big screen version.
- You're from Medvedkovo?
- Yes.
[Medvedkovo is a bedroom district]
[in the north-eastern part of Moscow]
- And you're the Director of Product Management
at Google?
- Yes.
- This is the famous free food!
They feed the dogs too
by the way.
- They do?
- Yep.
The dog has a badge.
They give it a badge so you can bring it
to work so it's not home alone.
[ANDREY DORONICHEV]
[37 years old]
[Director of Product Management at Google]
They give it a badge so you can bring it
to work so it's not home alone.
[ANDREY DORONICHEV]
[37 years old]
[Director of Product Management at Google]
- Really?
- It's simple.
[ANDREY DORONICHEV]
[37 years old]
[Director of Product Management at Google]
You wanna stay at work for longer,
but your dog misses you at home.
[ANDREY DORONICHEV]
[37 years old]
[Created the YouTube mobile app]
You wanna stay at work for longer,
but your dog misses you at home.
[ANDREY DORONICHEV]
[37 years old]
[Created the YouTube mobile app]
This way, it's around you,
it's got food.
This is like another way to tether
people to Google's offices?
Not exactly "tether." It's more like
a comfortable environment
so you don't worry
about trivial shit.
Do you come here?
Of course. I eat here every day.
You're in shape. The guy
from PR is also in shape.
How do you do it?
There's so much chow around,
but people somehow stay in shape.
So there's a thing
called Google 15.
When you start at Google, you usually
quickly gain 15 pounds. It's like 7 kilos.
That's exactly what happened to me.
You gotta get back in shape
afterward... actively.
There's a gym right over there,
behind the food trucks.
See the next building? That's where
people go to run and lift weights.
You know?
In my estimate, around 98%,
maybe 99% of employees in Russia
will see this and raise their brows.
They don't know what's the point
of all this free stuff.
Can you explain?
If you wanna create
something unusual,
something much greater
than what's predictable,
you need an unusual environment.
You need to create an environment
where people can focus on creating,
inventing,
thinking outside the box,
et cetera.
Each step you take in this direction works
towards your company's capitalization.
Therefore,
by reducing the need to think
about all sorts of nonsense,
you increase the amount of time people
can dedicated to solving problems.
Do you though?
Doesn't it relax people?
Well, the thing is, you hire people
whose purpose in life is creating.
They just need the environment.
That's why I'm here.
I just really wanted to do my work
and I found the best
environment to do it
without worrying about
anything else.
This is just inappropriate.
Very much appropriate!
You see...
Here's the thing.
[Sergey Brin and Larry Page met at Stanford]
[and founded Google when they were 25.]
[In early spring of 2020, Forbes estimated Brin's net]
[worth at $49.1 billion and Page's, at $50.9 billion]
These guys, Sergey and Larry,
when they founded this company,
[Sergey Brin and Larry Page met at Stanford]
[and founded Google when they were 25.]
[In early spring of 2020, Forbes estimated Brin's net]
[worth at $49.1 billion and Page's, at $50.9 billion]
they drew inspiration
from their school.
I.e. Stanford.
- You've been there, right?
- Yeah.
- They have courts too.
This is basically the climate
of a college campus:
free exchange of knowledge,
you're relaxed,
you're a student,
you can play some volleyball, read some books,
write a report and so on.
Graduates would stream here
to build great things.
They created an environment for them that was
as close as possible to something like Stanford.
The second major influence,
I think, was the Burning Man.
It's a crazy festival that Sergey
and Larry had also gone to.
[You can find a detailed video about the Burning Man]
[by clicking the link in the description]
It's a crazy festival that Sergey
and Larry had also gone to.
[You can find a detailed video about the Burning Man]
[by clicking the link in the description]
The free bicycles, the free food.
[You can find a detailed video about the Burning Man]
[by clicking the link in the description]
This whole culture of giving.
Like, let's all give as much as possible,
and something great will come out.
It's basically like
"from each according to his ability,
to each according to his needs."
The more you give,
and if a crowd of people is doing the same,
you'll get something great as a result.
[SILICON VALLEY → APARTMENT]
You know what's the hardest part
of editing episodes like this one?
Being reminded that there are
things like airports,
airplanes, flights
and other things that used to take you
to places other than home.
Even if you love your home
very much.
The only saviors, you guys,
are this couch
and YouTube that you can
watch on this couch.
Here are two YouTube channels
to help you stay sane
during this quarantine.
The first channel is called Arzamas.
Many will once again make fun of me, saying that
it took me until 2020 to discover internet,
but yes, only in April of this year, I first watched
two great videos on the Arzamas channel:
Ancient Rome in 20 Minutes
and Ancient Greece.
They're history lectures
fitting the year 2020.
Channel number two. One of the funniest
rumors about our creative crew was this:
"Dud' produces the Tender Editor channel."
The Tender Editor channel
has only one producer.
And her name is
Tatyana Mingalimova,
the wonderful, tender lady,
who used to be our editor
for the longest time
but then started her own thing.
Last year, "her own thing" materialized
as the show Girl Friends.
(show intro made with mouth sounds)
When I hear Tanechka
confessing the fact that there's
little sex in her life
and exploring this as an issue,
in those moments I realize
I'm a real prude
who's embarrassed
to say the word "sex."
So, girls...
(blows a kiss) Artiom!
...godspeed!
I'll be watching these and other
channels sitting on this very couch
on my new TV, Philips 7303,
which I got from, guess who,
my buddies from ELDORADO!
(Dud') That's you?!
That's... YOU?!
While we were setting up the TV,
we remembered
[*Both cameramen of the crew are called Sergey.]
that Seriogas* were also
famous content creators
and used to make videos
about rope jumping.
What did the nightmare
of all Russian fridges
Sergey Linkov look like in 2012?
Is that him? That's him!
(laughs)
I thought I had a big head!
Serionia!
You actually jumped?
Ho-ly shit!
I already watch the first two channels.
This one, I'll start watching on this TV.
It has everything you need:
full Smart TV functionality
with the Android TV
operating system,
easy navigation, intuitive interface
and a wide selection of applications.
Stylish design.
4K UHD resolution.
Unique and super handy
Ambilight feature.
It's main effect: the picture
appears larger
thanks to Ambilight filling the space
around the TV with a colored halo.
This feature works particularly well at night
if you enjoy watching TV in the dark.
It substantially reduces eye stress.
It also has a special Lounge mode
where Ambilight works even without video,
simply filling the room with mood light.
There's a link under this,
not the couch, video!
Smash that link below
to get 15% off with the promo code
"БУДЬВТЕМЕ15" (STAYINTHELOOP15)
when purchasing this
or any other Philips TVs.
While my buddies from Eldorado will deliver it
to your place safely and free of charge,
so you're entertained
during quarantine.
Hold on, guys!
[APARTMENT → SILICON VALLEY]
(doorbell rings)
Attack!
(footsteps)
(Dud') What if someone
gets injured?
(Doronichev) Immediately with
the liabilities, huh?
Yes!
(Doronichev laughs)
It's not functionally sound!
Some guy's car parked outside
broke down.
- This entire house is yours?
- All mine.
Yes.
We're in San Francisco.
- Three-story house. Yours.
- Yes.
But it's millions of dollars.
It was much cheaper
than what it costs now,
because I got it
in a really bad condition.
I got it for $2.5 million.
And renovated it?
Yes. Renovation wasn't cheap either.
- Is it mortgage?
- Yes. I owe money.
If you don't owe anyone,
no one trusts you in America.
You need to owe someone.
How does a guy from Medvedkovo become
the Director of Product Management of all of Google?
First, you need to try and create
something in Medvedkovo.
You'll probably end up
with something bad.
Then you'll need to want to create something
again and move out of Medvedkovo.
My journey was long.
I went from Medvedkovo to Prague,
from Prague to Dublin,
from Dublin to London,
and eventually moved here.
Let me try and shorten
that story.
- You have a programmer's diploma.
- Yes.
- You created the site Tapok.ru.
In the era of simple
mobile phones...
- ...if you wanted the Boomer tune on your phone,
you had to do it on Tapok.ru.
- Yes.
And it made you a lot of money.
Not a lot, but some money.
You said you could buy
a car every day?
Not every day. I could buy one
every month.
- You could buy a new car every month.
- Yes. A shitty one.
- What?
- A shitty car every month.
- After that, you moved to Prague.
- Yes.
[Doronichev moved to Prague in 2006]
Why?
Because I realized
I had no one to learn from
how to make something truly big.
I wanted to...
Tapok. ru wasn't much different
from mobile YouTube.
It was a mobile service that
gave you access to content
like videos, music.
But on old phones.
On old phones. But that's not the point.
The point is that it was...
Essentially the same idea
took the shape of
"Send a short message to..."
This sort of low-scale
business operation
without much of an idea behind it.
When I realized that the same idea
could play a significant role
on a global scale
in how the world operates,
when I saw that this was real,
I realized I couldn't do it
living where I lived at the time.
I recently re-watched this video.
We had someone film us
at school in 9th grade.
They asked us what
we wanted to do.
I had read some nifty book
and said that I wanted to develop business
strategies for companies for money.
I had little understand of what that meant
at the time, but it sounded cool.
Eventually, it did become my job.
I worked for Cisco.
It's a tech company.
[Cisco is a multinational company that develops]
[network equipment for major organizations]
[and telecommunications firms]
It's a tech company.
[Cisco is a multinational company that develops]
[network equipment for major organizations]
[and telecommunications firms]
Then I went to study
in Scotland, got back
[Cisco is a multinational company that develops]
[network equipment for major organizations]
[and telecommunications firms]
and started trying to launch
various businesses.
[Cisco is a multinational company that develops]
[network equipment for major organizations]
[and telecommunications firms]
Then I realized that...
After another failure, one of my
friends came to me and said:
"I already have a working business."
"Can you help me raise
money to expand?"
"We have incoming orders."
"We just need the money to produce."
I agreed to help them. I put together a nice
presentation, they got the money.
I thought: cool.
I didn't ask for money, but the way,
but they paid me.
They paid me well over what
I earned in six months.
I thought: "Wow! Why do I even
go to work?"
I continued to do this in the background.
This got me introduced to Sergey Solonin.
My college mate's father
introduced me.
I came to him with
an investment offer.
- He said: "I don't understand this stuff..."
- Sergey Solonin from Qiwi?
Yeah. "You want Serioga. He's smart.
He's into technology. Talk to him."
[Sergey Solonin, co-founder of the Qiwi mobile]
[payment platform. Net worth according]
[to Forbes-2015 ranking — $400 million]
Yeah. "You want Serioga. He's smart.
He's into technology. Talk to him."
[Sergey Solonin, co-founder of the Qiwi mobile]
[payment platform. Net worth according]
[to Forbes-2015 ranking — $400 million]
I go to the address he gave me, Petrovskiy alley,
and find this super expensive palace.
Just... pure luxury.
Expensive pictures on walls.
$100,000 leather couch.
I don't know how much it was worth,
but it looked ridiculous.
Sitting on the couch was this guy
in track pants and a wifebeater,
with greasy hair,
like mine right now,
and red eyes of someone
who hasn't slept in three days,
reading something.
He checks out my 15-page
presentation,
just flips through it like this, asks three
questions about its weakest points
and says: "Total garbage.
Redo it and come back."
I thought: "Wow. This guy is SMART."
I redid it. Came back.
He checked it out and said:
"Better. I won't give you any money,
but I like you."
"Let's open a fund."
I knew what funds were and how they
worked, 'cause I studied it in college.
I thought my journey to a venture
fund would take ten years.
Instead, it took one
chance meeting.
You moved to Prague?
I moved... elsewhere.
To me, it was all "overseas."
I moved overseas. I moved in search
of a crowd I could learn from.
Prague wasn't the place.
Wait. What was the idea?
You moved:
Charles Bridge,
Staropramen beer...
What did you do over there?
There, I lost the part of me
I was always familiar with.
It was just a way to drag myself
out of my old environment.
- Oh. So you moved elsewhere not
planning to do anything particular?
- Yeah.
No. I moved to work. I moved to learn.
I moved to search.
I just didn't know
where to go yet.
I had the "Muscovite's globe": MKAD,
beyond it, Siberia,
and then the overseas.
More or less.
I didn't know how the Silicon Valley
was different from London
or how London was
different from Prague.
I just moved elsewhere
to make some sort of step.
If you don't know what to do,
make one step.
You studied there?
No. I tried to start a business.
Didn't quite work out.
I lost all the money I had
'cause I was stupid.
Ended up in a tough situation...
which is really motivating.
"All the money"
was how much exactly?
At the time, I had...
Leaving the country,
I had around $100,000.
How did you lost them?
Bad investment, in Russia.
- In what?
- In my relative's business.
He was doing some shady things.
Didn't work out in the end.
- You said you ate sausage clippings there?
- Yeah, I did.
What are sausage clippings?
When they slice meats
at the deli counter,
they end up with end bits.
They actually sell them.
You can ask if they
have leftovers that...
end pieces of sausage.
They're sold real cheap.
If you can't afford sausage, you can buy
these clippings. They're much cheaper.
I had a daily budget of 200 rubles
for a family of three people.
- You said 300.
- Or was it 300?
Yeah, 200 korunas or 300 rubles.
Right.
How did you survive?
Humbly.
Humbly, but with a lot
of determination.
You know? With a purpose.
How did Prague lead to Google?
I wrote a letter to Google.
I read books, I wanted to understand.
I moved to learn.
I moved to learn how to create
large-scale products,
how to make something
like iTunes.
iPod had just come out
at the time.
And... I started reading books about
the founders of some major companies:
Dell, Oracle, Microsoft.
I read one about Google.
And... it blew me away.
I realized that
someone had built a culture
I wanted to build myself.
I had no idea how to build it.
I wanted to learn and I realized that
I wanted to learn from these people.
So I sent them an email.
- An email?
- Yes.
I sent an email to jobs@google.com
that said
something like: "Guys, you're
neglecting the mobile phones."
"Mobile phones are the future."
"Everyone here in Russia
is on mobile phones."
"I know how to do it.
Please, hire me and I'll do it."
They didn't reply. Obviously.
- They didn't reply?
- They didn't.
They didn't reply after a month,
after two months.
I kept looking for contacts
to reach them.
Eventually, they replied.
I couldn't find anyone. They just replied
themselves several months later.
- Sounds kinda unreal.
- Totally.
- Like emailing the Kremlin.
- It was totally unreal.
I don't know of another
story like that.
I still fund it really weird
that it worked out.
The stars must've aligned.
Why do you think they replied?
I think I got lucky.
I believe every success
involves a lot of effort,
many failures and the perseverance
to overcome those failures,
but realistically, you'll always
need some luck.
They called me after all
the interviews and said:
"We have a job opening for you,
but it's not in Prague."
"It's in Dublin."
At that point, it no longer made any difference.
On my globe, they were practically the same.
So I went to Dublin.
What are these holes?
They're ground squirrels
called gophers.
There's a ton of them out here.
It's the wilds.
They're prey to eagles in the sky,
roaming foxes,
mountain lions and coyotes.
- You warned us not to let your cat out. Why?
- They'll eat him.
Down here, cats... None of ours
ever got eaten, thankfully.
Friends and neighbors lost 'em just like that.
They run away and...
Cats are naturally cocky. If it sees
a raccoon, it'll start a fight with it.
A raccoon will kill a cat
just like that.
Larger animals will too,
mostly coyotes.
How do you let your
kids out to play?
They don't attack children.
I believe, in the last five years, only one
child got attacked by a mountain lion.
Just don't let your kids
stray too far alone.
They don't come near houses.
If you have a child with you,
you want to pick up the child.
The animal will see you
as a single large entity.
Who lives here besides
your family?
We live on the top floor.
My family, kids.
One the second floor, we have several
business owners, all Russian-speaking.
It's a great little gang.
There's four of them.
On the ground floor, we have
an assorted group of people.
Why are you offering
them shelter?
They're renting.
- Oh, they pay you money?
- Yeah.
It kinda appears like Erlich's place
from the show Silicon Valley.
(Doronichev laughs)
It does!
Guy offers startuppers housing in exchange
for 10% of their startup's capital.
Do you too take 10%?
No. I agreed to much less.
I put money into one of
the second-floor startups.
I bought some shares from Dumik.
I was one of the first to invest in his Chatfuel.
Only him though.
So you're just offering
guys shelter?
No. I gave him some money for the company,
I invested in his company,
and also he pays me rent.
I use the money to pay off
the mortgage.
Can you tell us about the two guys
sitting behind Serioga and I?
I believe they're both really
smart and talented guys
from the former Soviet Union,
Belarus and Russia,
who are living proof that
you can come here alone,
with empty pockets,
and create multimillion-dollar companies
with nothing but hard work and your vision.
Alone.
I watched this happen
for both of them.
Both Dima Dumik and Mikita
created huge companies
from scratch
right before my eyes.
I'd look at them and think:
"What am I doing with my life?"
For the last two days,
Andrey has been preparing me,
saying: "I have your carbon copy
living in my house."
[DMITRIY DUMIK]
[34 years old]
Let's look in the camera.
[DMITRIY DUMIK]
[Founded Chatfuel, a platform for creating]
[chatbots for the Facebook Messenger]
And now sideways.
[Founded Chatfuel, a platform for creating]
[chatbots for the Facebook Messenger]
We do look alike!
[Founded Chatfuel, a platform for creating]
[chatbots for the Facebook Messenger]
We do look alike!
- You too were born in '86?
- Yes.
- But you're from Taganrog.
Okay. It's a little bit spooky.
But okay, let the audience decide.
Can you explain in super simple
terms what chatbots are?
Chatbots are... You're talking
to someone in the Messenger, right?
- Yeah?
- You can similarly talk to a business.
You can ask questions,
request help our support,
while a business can communicate
with you, engage you, send you GIFs.
They'll ask:
"Yura, what are you into?"
"You're going to San Francisco. We're
having an event. You should come."
It's super personalized communication.
- But I need to subscribe?
- Yes.
And it'll tlalk...
(butchers the word, gurgles)
- It'll talk to me on Facebook?
- Yes.
Not on Telegram or..?
There are other platforms that work
with Telegram and other messengers.
- Yours, only on Facebook?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Right. How do you monetize it?
Businesses pay a fee to use
the platform to send messages.
The more users you want to reach
the more you pay, on a monthly basis.
- Some of your clients are Uber...
- Yes.
- Coca-Cola...
- And even Golden State.
- Yes.
[The Golden State Warriors are a professional]
[basketball team based in San Francisco]
Assuming I've become your client,
how much do I pay?
$15 to start. Up to 1000 users.
Right. What's the cap?
There is no cap.
But the biggest clients pay
tens of thousands of dollars.
- Tens of thousands?
- Yeah. A month.
Okay. What's your monthly profit?
Uhm...
I can't announce it publicly,
but it's in hundreds of thousands
of dollars.
- That's profit?
- No, that's our revenue.
- Gotcha.
- But you make a profit?
- Yeah.
Yes, we have a positive
operating margin.
- You haven't sold the company yet?
- No.
- Andrey says that if you do,
you'll be a multimillionaire.
- It's a possibility.
- Mikita Mikado.
- Yeah.
[MIKITA MIKADO]
[33 years old]
(both laugh)
[MIKITA MIKADO]
[Created the PandaDoc]
[document automation service]
- Are you Japanese?
- No, I'm Belarusian. Belarusian.
[Created the PandaDoc]
[document automation service]
You said it so cute!
We Belarusians are very cute.
You said it in such a voice
that I just want to hug you!
(laughing) "I'm Belarusian!"
Why "Mikado"?
- When I was 19, I came to America
for the first time.
- Right?
As part of a student
exchange program.
What was it?
Work and Travel USA.
I came over and was lodged
at this Japanese guy's house.
The Japanese guy used to call me
Mikita, Makaka, Mikaka,
Mikado...
That last one sort of stuck.
- Then they launched LinkedIn.
- Yeah.
Back then, using your real name
on a social network was kinda scary.
I registered as Mikita Mikado
and optimized this LinkedIn account
for certain search engine inquiries.
"Website development Hawaii."
I lived in Hawaii at the time.
People started contacting me.
I started getting business.
I made a business card
for Mikita Mikado.
I started signing contracts,
making and selling websites.
I was just using it more and more.
- 'Cause my last name is impossible
to pronounce in America.
- What is it?
TSE-PLA-VU-K-HA-U.
- See?
- That's in Belarusian. What is it in Russian?
Teplouhov.
- Oh! Teplouhov?
- Yeah, yeah.
Wow. Complicated.
- I thought only popular singers
used stage names.
- Well, now you know.
- Programmers too.
- Programmers do too, yeah.
Damn!
What does your business do?
- Ever signed a document? A contract?
- Yes.
We make it so you can sign
documents without paper,
without couriers, mailing documents
and so on.
- And they have the same legal power
as documents signed on paper?
- Yes!
- For real?
- It works.
You can test it.
- So we can sign documents remotely?
- Yeah. Uhm...
Important...
It's worth noting that
it works in the US and...
- ...countries with...
- Electronic document flow?
Not just electronic document flow,
but also e-signature laws.
- Oh. They don't exist in Russia.
- They're a little different.
When I came to Google, they didn't
offer me to work with mobile phones.
It was all only starting
back then.
For a while, I worked
on some other things.
Only about two years later, they put
together a mobile team in London
that made mobile apps
for all of their products.
- What year was that?
- This was 2008.
- 2008?
- Yeah.
They trusted you with something because
you did this mobile thing back in Russia?
They trusted me with something because
no one thought it was important.
They thought it was nonsense.
But how? This is 2008.
Everyone has phones.
Couldn't they see that..?
At that point, people hadn't
yet connected the dots
in their heads that the internet would be
something you carry around in your pocket.
Everyone though the internet was:
you come home, turn on your computer
and go online using
a modem or a wire.
Mobile was for calling and
sending short messages.
Maybe occasional email. That was the pinnacle
of communications technology.
The idea that people would
watch movies on their phones
or play online games
sounded like unrealistic futurism.
You said you specifically asked them to let
you develop the mobile app for YouTube?
To be honest, when I joined
their mobile team,
all the good products had already been
assigned to more talented folks.
Stuff like Gmail, the Google search itself,
they were already assigned to someone.
Only leftovers no one
else wanted remained.
YouTube was one
of the things that...
I mean, no one cared about the browser
version either, did they?
All it had were some dogs on
skateboards and similar garbage.
I was the new guy.
They offered me a choice of several
not very successful products.
When they offered YouTube...
I knew that Tapok that I made back
in Russia was almost the same thing.
I knew that people would watch
video on their phones
because they used to BUY them
on my site.
People from backwater towns used to
buy Crazy Frog videos through SMS
to simply go: "Hey, man!
Check it out! Crazy Frog!"
This was my first project,
a mobile app that let you
use your phone to...
You're speaking.
There's a presentation.
It let you change slides, record
your voice and broadcast it.
- This didn't exist prior?
- Nope.
- Right. It didn't take off?
- Crashed and burned.
Right. Then?
Then I... We'd raised money for it,
venture money.
- Which you didn't return?
- No, of course not.
Yeah. The project didn't take off.
I realized no one's ever giving us money again.
I met my partner,
the now CTO of my current company.
We figured we had
one last chance.
We either do something or I'm just
not cut out for startups
and I should go back
to corporations.
[Before creating startups, Dumik spent]
[5 years at Procter & Gamble]
I had to call my parents.
[Before creating startups, Dumik spent]
[5 years at Procter & Gamble]
I'd been supporting
myself for a while,
but at 25, I had to call them to borrow
several thousand dollars.
You know, "this is my last chance."
And it took off.
It was a mobile app, Myata.
And... We knew there was
no room for failure.
We were two people. We did everything
ourselves: coding, design, product.
Myata was the thing that assembled
a feed based on your interests?
- Yes. It's an app...
- For VK.
- Yes. Yeah.
Okay. What do you mean by "took off?"
It made you money?
Yes. It made us money.
"Took off" means that
when we launched on App Store,
we reached #2 on App Store.
We had 300,000 downloads
in a week.
And we started monetizing it
with ads.
How much did it make you?
We sold it. We sold
the Russian version.
We had a Russian version.
We decided to make a global one.
We sold the Russian version. For not too
much, several hundred thousand dollars.
We started working on the global
version, and it was a struggle.
They use Facebook. It has its own
rules and restrictions.
That's when Pasha Durov
posted in his blog,
saying: "Guys, we're launching
chatbots on the Telegram platform."
I call Tioma and go: "Hey, wake up."
He's in Moscow, it's night. I'm here.
"Tioma, wake up. This is the next big thing.
We need to make something."
A team of developers needs to make it
so there's a YouTube icon on the screen.
How many years?
What are the steps?
Well, there are YouTube servers
somewhere out there
hosting videos and sending them
via the internet to some device.
The device must be powerful
enough to decode them.
The connection must be fast
enough to download them.
And then this app needs to work on this
small device with its small processor
to download videos, to offer you choice
of videos and different menus.
They key piece of course is the player that
decodes and plays videos in real time.
At the time, this was a fairly
complicated task,
because we were developing it
from scratch for those old phones.
The first app was actually designed for
Nokias and old Windows PDAs.
It didn't work. It was awful.
During the first year, I thought:
"What am I doing here?"
"It probably won't work."
When did you realize
that it will?
When Android came out.
The player worked on the first
Android that we launched.
[The first version of Android]
[came out in September of 2008]
The player worked on the first
Android that we launched.
[The first version of Android]
[came out in September of 2008]
This was yet another prophetic but
seemingly idiotic move,
because there were zero Androids
and millions of Nokias.
But nothing worked on Nokia, while on Android
we could get it to work.
I only had, like, two or three
engineers at that moment.
We decided to go for it
and switched over to Android.
And later iPhone.
And it worked.
When we got our first 100,000
views on mobile phones,
obviously, the site youtube.com
had millions of views by that point,
but mobile users had cumulatively added
100,000 to that number, and we went to a bar,
I bought all the engineers beer.
We were joking around:
hey, 100,000 views is free beer, cool,
but what do we get for one million?
I said: "Guys, one day, mobile YouTube
will be bigger than that other YouTube."
"When this happens..."
My engineering partner says: "When this
happens, you'll take us to Hawaii."
I said:
"Yeah, I'll take you to Hawaii."
I did.
When did this happen?
This was somewhere
around 2013 or 2014.
Today, most people watch
YouTube on their phones?
I can guarantee you that most people
watching this video of us
are most likely watching it
in the app I helped launch.
(title card music)
(outdoor noise)
(muffled voices)
(wind, passing cars)
(Davidov) Gamedev is a huge industry.
Just like filmmaking.
Gamedev is bigger than filmmaking.
[The video game industry made ~$140 billion in 2019]
[The film game industry made ~$100 billion in 2019]
Guys from Briansk creating
3D animation for movies
and Russian freelancers working
out of Goa doing the same thing,
they're making good money,
because it costs a lot.
We create content for games,
movies, media and TV shows,
mostly for California, but we have
clients all over the world.
[MAKSIM MIHEYENKO]
[Founded the 5518 Studios digital art studio]
Our headquarters is in LA.
Production, in Russia.
[MAKSIM MIHEYENKO]
[Founded the 5518 Studios digital art studio]
But we also create teams:
[MAKSIM MIHEYENKO]
[Worked on art for World of Tanks and Call of Duty]
Brazil, Australia, CIS.
[MAKSIM MIHEYENKO]
[Worked on art for World of Tanks and Call of Duty]
We have people from all over, because you can no longer say that CoD was made in the US.
It's made by the Vietnamese, Indians,
Russians, Ukrainians, Americans, Brits.
Same with World of Tanks.
Same with other projects.
They're now global corporations.
Just like us. We have
people from all over.
For example, someone's
making a video game,
they hire you to create some of the art
and pay you to do it.
We help large companies
produce content on time,
because games are becoming more
and more complex and expansive.
You can't produce everything in-house.
That's why they delegate art and coding
to talents from around the world.
We help them with that.
What if we decide that our show
needs some graphics?
Say, for our geographic routes.
We want a super map
that shows us
going from Moscow to San Fran,
to the Valley, to the towns.
How much will it cost us?
Depends on task description.
If you know exactly what you want,
it's figure A.
If you go, "Maks, let's change this part," it's B.
If you wanna redo the whole thing, it's C.
Let's say, we know exactly.
This costs anywhere from
$10,000 to $100,000.
But it depends on
whether we can show it,
whether you let us display it,
and if you're a pleasant
person to work with.
Besides, we want a client
like Yura on our portfolio,
so we could do it
for a cup of coffee.
You're from Ulyanovsk.
How did you end up all the way
out here, in the Silicon Valley?
I started working in ninth grade.
First with Russians, then quickly
switched to Americans.
- I have been working with Americans
since ninth grade.
- Doing what?
I started out as a designer.
I made websites, logos, applications.
Then I switched to digital art.
I created art for many games:
Call of Duty, Fallout, World of Tanks.
I started out as an artist,
then senior artist,
then I supervised some people,
then I started my own company.
For World of Tanks,
we made a ton of tanks,
environmental objects,
barrels, airplanes.
Lots of stuff.
Then you see it in the game. And millions
of people are buying this tank with real money.
The feeling's orgasmic.
You're thinking: "Fuck!"
What did it look like?
You're in Ulyanovsk,
in your apartment...
[*Low-cost standardized apartment building]
[mass-built from mid-'60s to '80s.]
- Hrushovka*?
- Yeah.
In Ulyanovsk. How did you draw?
Did you have a special tablet?
Yeah, I got a tablet. I didn't initially.
I just had a mouse.
I'd draw with it, super poorly.
I'd look at other people's works and
wondered what's wrong with my hand:
why are my works so... crooked.
- Then I realized I needed to get a tablet
that cost my entire salary.
- Yeah?
I saved up, my parents pitched in too,
and I bought myself a tablet.
And away we went! Turned out, drawing
on your computer was super convenient!
Wait, do you have any artistic talents
or was it formulaic stuff?
I studied at Kuliok.
That's our University of Arts
in Ulyanovsk.
I was a very bad student,
actually.
And I'm ashamed, because instead
of painting art and understanding Ayvazovskiy,
I'd draw all these zombies, and monsters,
and women with big boobs,
because I drew inspiration
from games.
Teachers would give me C's.
I'd go home, draw my stuff,
and the Americans would go:
"Dude, great! We love you!"
I was like: "So am I an A or a C student?
What am I, really?"
My big advantage was
that I didn't argue.
I think we still have
this issue in Russia
where we believe that getting
feedback is always shitty.
I go: "Yura, you need different jeans."
You go: "Piss off, Maks."
Something like that.
Many act this way at home.
I'd go: "Great feedback.
Thank you."
I knew I was inexperienced
and they knew better.
I didn't argue.
I just said: "Let's do it this way. Or that way."
Or: "Here's a couple of options."
'Cause Americans are often
super busy
and they just go: "Hey, can you make us
a tank for Call of Duty?"
You say: "Okay. Any references,
pictures and stuff?"
They go: "We leave it to you."
Basically, our subsequent work
needs to make them go:
"Option A. With this track.
Tomorrow. Go."
We need to meet them
halfway sometimes.
Others often go: "I need a detailed task
description. I can't work without one."
"Give me a detailed
task description."
Clients often don't have
time for that.
Your point is, being proactive
and self-reliant rules?
Being proactive, self-reliant, able to predict
what the client wants,
and giving options are the things
that I find help a lot.
When you're not sure what they want,
make two options. Or better yet, three.
And say:
"Here's what you asked. Here's my vision.
And here's a crazy third option."
The client will appreciate it.
- (Dud') This is the entire valley?
- (Davidov) Yes. This is the entire Silicon Valley.
You can see its every
corner from here.
(Dud') Palo Alto, Mountain View.
That was is San Jose.
San Jose is where the Valley started.
The semiconductor companies
started out there.
[Fairchild Semiconductor designed integrated circuits and]
[was one of the Valley's biggest companies in the 1960s]
Fairchild Semiconductor. Those guys
would get military grants.
[Fairchild Semiconductor designed integrated circuits and]
[was one of the Valley's biggest companies in the 1960s]
They made the first computers,
exclusively for the military and NASA.
[Semiconductor companies produce electronic]
[devices like circuit boards, transistors, LEDs]
That's where life sort of started.
[Semiconductor companies produce electronic]
[devices like circuit boards, transistors, LEDs]
Stanford graduates finally had
a place to go to make big bucks.
It all started in the '50s,
with Stanford
and
the super liberal vision of
then head of the university
who began to sponsor his
graduates, lending them
[Wallace Sterling was the President of Stanford University]
[from 1949 to 1968. The Research Park was spearheaded]
[by Frederick Terman (it was his influence that led Stanford]
[graduates to create Hewlett-Packard in the 1930s)].
[In the 1950s, the university leased some of its land to]
[high-tech companies and expanded its operations to get]
[government grants from the Department of Defense.]
[Terman is considered the father of the Silicon Valley]
who began to sponsor his
graduates, lending them
[Wallace Sterling was the President of Stanford University]
[from 1949 to 1968. The Research Park was spearheaded]
[by Frederick Terman (it was his influence that led Stanford]
[graduates to create Hewlett-Packard in the 1930s)].
[In the 1950s, the university leased some of its land to]
[high-tech companies and expanded its operations to get]
[government grants from the Department of Defense.]
[Terman is considered the father of the Silicon Valley]
offices or space
to use as offices,
[Wallace Sterling was the President of Stanford University]
[from 1949 to 1968. The Research Park was spearheaded]
[by Frederick Terman (it was his influence that led Stanford]
[graduates to create Hewlett-Packard in the 1930s)].
[In the 1950s, the university leased some of its land to]
[high-tech companies and expanded its operations to get]
[government grants from the Department of Defense.]
[Terman is considered the father of the Silicon Valley]
and was essentially the pioneer
of this whole venture capitalism idea.
That's how Hewlett-Packard
was founded.
[Venture capital is risky investments]
[in brand new types of business]
The very idea of nurturing talent
[Venture capital is risky investments]
[in brand new types of business]
and believing in it so much that you give
them money so they try to create something
in this brand new, totally foreign
at the time field of
semiconductors, processors and so on
started out in Stanford.
Then the inventor of
the transistor came here.
He created a company,
it was fairly despotic, I mean,
he was a fairly despotic genius,
[Company in question is Fairchild Semiconductor]
[with its founder William Shockley]
it was fairly despotic, I mean,
he was a fairly despotic genius,
[Company in question is Fairchild Semiconductor]
[with its founder William Shockley]
and he ended up losing
eight of his key engineers.
These eight key engineers who earned
the nickname "the traitorous eight"
actually created the second super
important element of the Valley,
the flow of ideas,
the tolerance for the idea that people may
leave your company to start their own,
and it's okay.
They all left and founded
all the key companies.
Intel, AMD and others
were in one way or another
fathered by those eight dudes.
Stanford is basically the cradle
of the Silicon Valley.
Its students went on to become founders of Google,
senior execs at Facebook, Microsoft, EA, LinkedIn.
They all studied at or at least
got accepted to Stanford.
- (Dud') But didn't all graduate?
- (Miheyenko) MANY of them didn't.
Let me try and outline the history
of founding of Stanford very quickly.
[ILYA STREBULAYEV]
[44 years old]
[Professor of Finance at the Stanford University]
[Graduate School of Business]
There was a rich man who made
a lot of money on railroads.
[ILYA STREBULAYEV]
[44 years old]
[Professor of Finance at the Stanford University]
[Graduate School of Business]
His son died at 15
from typhoid fever.
And he decided to found
a university in his memory.
Is it true, that 150 years ago,
founding a university
in someone's memory
was a brow-raising decision?
It was, but not because it was
founded in someone's memory.
It raised brows because California
was a backwater state at the time.
The idea of creating something
bright in California
was hard to process.
Moreover, there already was
a university in California.
There was a university at the other
end of the San Francisco Bay,
one of the most respected
universities in America today,
University of California,
Berkeley
And this was a state university.
I think many laughed at Stanford
for trying to create something that
could compete with Berkeley.
And what's the point of a second
university in California?
A lot has changed
in the last 150 years!
A lot HAS changed.
And not in the last 150 years,
but probably much closer to now.
'Cause even around the time
World War II broke out,
I doubt the major East Coast
universities
like Harvard, Princeton and Yale
saw a competitor in Stanford.
Then it all suddenly changed
in the span of 15 or 20 years.
The greatest garage in the Valley
is not Jobs' and Wozniak's garage,
but the Hewlett-Packard garage?
Yes. It was where it all started,
this whole culture.
Hewlett-Packard was the first operation
that Stanford sponsored.
That garage was where the seeds
of this culture were created.
A lot of other companies were later
started in garages, including Google.
Google started in
Susan Wojcicki's garage.
Today she's the CEO of YouTube.
(blows a kiss)
Our queen!
- What's that behind you?
- That's the campus of the Stanford
Graduate School of Business.
You mentioned a garage for startups?
Yeah. Startup Garage.
- What do they do there?
- Or the Stanford Venture Studio.
It's very interesting.
About 5 or 6 years ago,
we decided to open what we called
the Startup Garage,
where over the course of
one semester or one quarter,
Stanford uses the Quarter System
with the summer quarter off,
over the course one quarter, our students
at the Graduate Business School
could practice actual entrepreneurship.
Over the course of a quarter,
they could gather into small groups,
organize their own startups,
discuss different ideas,
get assistance from our alumni,
[Angel investors support]
[startups in their earliest stages]
angel investors, venture capitalists,
professors and so on.
[Angel investors support]
[startups in their earliest stages]
We didn't initially intend for these
startups to become real startups.
The idea was to let first- and second-year
students to try their hand
and get a feel,
and obtain certain skills required
for becoming entrepreneurs.
Initially, we believed this was
a purely educational process.
Just another program.
We have a lot of wonderful,
informative programs.
But in these 5 or 6 years,
everything changed.
Turned out, at this stage, students
can band together for just one quarter,
students from the business,
engineering and medical schools,
come up with an interesting idea
and tinker with it a little
without getting any sort of money,
any financing,
or assistance from
the Stanford University,
for just one quarter,
and in an insignificant number of cases
this leads to a real startup.
There are now real firms that
came out of this Startup Garage.
And they actually make money?
They've raised some serious money
from serious venture capitalists,
and some of them now
cost billions of dollars.
(man) Oh wow!
- (Dud') Hey! Hi.
- Hi. Tolik.
- Tolik, what are you doing here?
- Me? I...
- (Dud') Is that a check from your investor?
You all set?
- Yeah!
(Dud') Oh yeah? Nice!
- No, what is that?
- It's actually a check to pay for my wife's
medical insurance.
- Really?
- Yeah. Costs an arm and a leg.
I got my PhD at Stanford.
Where are you from?
- I'm from Krasnodar.
- Right?
I spent a lot of time in Moscow,
moved to Norway,
went back to Moscow,
bailed and came here.
(Miheyenko) You're in IT too?
I'm a co-founder. Typical stuff
for these parts.
But what I actually do is...
I spent a lot of time doing
geological surveying.
Uh-huh?
I'm developing this combination
artificial intelligence for geology.
Why do you need AI in geology for?
For example, there's computer vision
currently used in autonomous cars
that lets them identify trees,
pedestrians, what have you.
But what's happening underground,
we don't know. At all.
We don't have a good scanner.
Let's say, I have information
that we can get from sources...
Without sending anything down?
No, no. For example, there's some
acoustic information from a scanner,
but it doesn't give us true information.
Like, it's not a universal truth,
it's not real information.
Some devices can use systems
like AI and computer vision
to interpret what's really
going on underground.
The dude we met at Stanford.
Do you know him?
Yeah. That's my brother's friend
who got inspired by his example and moved
here too. They live next to each other.
And he's launching a startup...
grounded in geology?
I hope he's make it, yeah.
That's what I love the most:
people with different backgrounds,
from all over the world
get inspired by this spirit
of entrepreneurship.
It's very easy to get stuck in
an environment where you think:
"Me, an entrepreneur? Nah.
You have to be someone's son."
"Or you have to be insane."
That's what I thought
back in Medvedkovo.
"No, this is crazy. Entrepreneurship?"
They move here, and it comes
so naturally here,
that every Uber driver is also
doing business on the side.
Every cashier in the supermarket.
How does entrepreneurship
benefit society?
I mean, why is it better than
working for the state?
Entrepreneurship improves
the stability of the society.
In my view, you want the economy
to look like a grape cluster:
lots of small sweet berries
that together form this big fruit.
When you have an economy
that's like a single watermelon,
if you drop it, the entire
watermelon's ruined.
Whereas when you're economy
is like a grape cluster,
you've got natural selection,
competition,
a ton of ideas being tested
at the same time.
You have this fluidity and adaptivity
that let society react quickly
to rapidly changing circumstances.
Without the internet,
economy was one way.
The internet came along, and a ton of
global businesses collapsed,
you know, these enormous beasts.
But then a ton of...
In a society where
entrepreneurship was normal,
a ton of new companies immediately
emerged in their place,
the future facebooks and googles
and other multi-billion
corporations,
in a world where...
I mean, in '92, none of them were close
to emerging or even possible.
(Dud') Dasha Navalnaya is studying
here since this year.
(Miheyenko) I read on the news.
Sadly, haven't seen her around.
There are a lot of Russian
students here, Chinese, Indian.
They get education here.
They become a part of the society
and they know it.
We have a lot of clients here,
and they show what Stanford is.
It's the spirit of entrepreneurship.
[*Moscow State University.]
It's not even about knowledge.
MSU* isn't any worse.
They teach you here that you can open
your own startup tomorrow,
come up to your dean
or your professor,
and they'll give you $5 million
in the initial investment round.
We have a friend named Tony.
He graduated from here.
He created a startup that
teaches children coding.
His math professor was his
first investor.
- Did the startup take off?
- Yes.
And the professor made millions?
He hasn't reached IPO yet.
He hasn't made any money yet,
but his shares did skyrocket.
[IPO (initial public offering) is initial sale of company]
[shares on the market to invite investors]
[or make money from the sale]
He hasn't made any money yet,
but his shares did skyrocket.
[IPO (initial public offering) is initial sale of company]
[shares on the market to invite investors]
[or make money from the sale]
'Cause they went into the second
investment round,
[IPO (initial public offering) is initial sale of company]
[shares on the market to invite investors]
[or make money from the sale]
and this Stanford professor...
They invest bits of their salary?
- Like, their savings?
- Their savings and the money they made
from other startups.
I wish I could come to my dean
in Ulyanovsk and go:
"Sir, could you spare a couple mil?
I have this dream project in the works..."
Sadly, that won't work
over there just yet.
If you're a professor
at Stanford University
or a student, or an employee
of the University,
and you get an idea,
the university offers you the opportunity
to develop this idea,
to take it out of the University walls
and commercialize this idea.
The University provides
ample assistance,
both formal and informal.
For example, with the help of numerous
alumni of the University
that help you develop this idea,
with advice and financially.
But most importantly,
the University has a culture
and a vision that these
initiatives are welcomed.
As a result, a lot of, for example, professors
of Stanford University have their own startups.
You mean they're investors?
No, no. They're founders of startups.
- Ohh!
- They create startups themselves.
I'll give you an example.
There was a professor at the Stanford
University that specialized in biochemistry.
He came with an idea in his lab
to create the so-called artificial meat.
Had he been a professor
at some other place,
this idea would've probably died
in terms of commercial application.
But by using his contacts,
by using the Stanford University,
he became the founder or
a co-founder of a startup,
raised substantial venture money,
and now his Impossible Foods is one of
the most successful companies out there.
[Impossible Foods was founded in 2011.]
[It has raised $1.2 billion as of March of 2020.]
[It produces plant-based meat products,]
[including burgers]
Is his still a professor?
[Impossible Foods was founded in 2011.]
[It has raised $1.2 billion as of March of 2020.]
[It produces plant-based meat products,]
[including burgers]
He continued to work as a professor
for many years.
[Impossible Foods was founded in 2011.]
[It has raised $1.2 billion as of March of 2020.]
[It produces plant-based meat products,]
[including burgers]
I believe he left the position
some time ago
and focused on his startup that's now
become a multibillion-dollar company.
But there are other examples where people
continue working as professors.
For example, my another colleague,
Daphne Koller,
a Computer Science professor,
who founded Coursera,
a very famous educational startup.
She works as a professor
at Stanford University.
I don't have any school expenses,
only living expenses,
'cause it's freaking
expensive here.
How come you're getting
free tuition?
Special talent?
No. Stanford just sponsors a lot of people
that come here and study for free.
They offer free tuition,
housing allowance...
In exchange for what?
What do you give them?
In exchange for me doing
my research here.
I also hold a research assistant
position here.
I mean, they do it in exchange
for Stanford...
- Stanford call themselves The Farm.
- Yeah?
Their idea is:
"You guys come here,
you're like saplings."
"We plant you, water you,
and share certain values with you."
Different values.
Cultural, social.
"Then spread out wherever you go
"and spread these values to other
people one way or another."
It's a sort of missionary work,
you could call it.
- Or soft power.
- Exactly, yes.
It's soft power.
Why does the Stanford University
support entrepreneurship?
Does the Stanford University
take a cut off its beneficiaries?
That's a great question.
Two questions, actually:
why and does it?
Taking a cut depends on how much of the resources
of the Stanford University were used.
I'll give you two examples.
In the '90s, two startups were created,
Google and Yahoo!
They were both created by students
of the Stanford University.
Google's founders used the University's
resources quite extensively.
Stanford came to the conclusion that
because this search engine was
an in-house Stanford project,
this technology belonged
to the Stanford University.
So Google bought the rights to
the technology from Stanford.
Yes, at some point in the past, Stanford owned
a considerable amount of Google's shares.
[Google was initially even hosted on]
[the university's domain, google.stanford.edu]
Yes, at some point in the past, Stanford owned
a considerable amount of Google's shares.
[Google was initially even hosted on]
[the university's domain, google.stanford.edu]
With Yahoo!, this was another Stanford
student, Jerry Yang,
[Google was initially even hosted on]
[the university's domain, google.stanford.edu]
but the kinds of University resources he'd used
were night hours and such,
and so, as far as I know,
Stanford University concluded that
university resources hadn't been used,
and so it wasn't involved
with Yahoo! shares.
But then what's the point
for the University?
The point for the university...
There's a number of reasons.
First, because it's a very
natural balance,
because lots of scientists care about
the application of their knowledge.
It's very important.
Because many European universities
treat entrepreneurship
very differently.
Over there, a professor sits
on a high mountain,
thinking and inventing
something great,
while someone else scuttles around at the foot
of the mountain , trying to put it to work.
Down here, it's very different
That's number one.
Two, we earlier discussed the interaction between
the scientific and the learning processes.
It's very important, because in all these
examples I brought up students often take part
in practical application of new
scientific knowledge.
Obviously, most of our students
don't become professors.
- Most of them head out into the so-called
real world.
- Yeah.
Thanks to first-hand experience of
applying the knowledge they get here
in interesting practical projects,
they can work in the real world with
a lot more responsibility and success.
And the monetary appeal is,
if you do become a millionaire,
you'll donate to them
as their graduate?
Absolutely.
Besides, lots of Stanford graduates are
VPs of a bunch of major companies.
They donate a ton of money on
research groups and their support.
- Including you?
- Yep. Precisely.
- Damn.
You know how much money they get
each year in donations?
- Who?
- You know the figure? Stanford.
- From their graduates.
- No.
- One billion bucks.
- Holy crap!
I tried to imagine this money.
It's freaking crazy!
One thing I found interesting about
the 18-year-olds that enroll here.
We choose a faculty once
and stick with it.
You pick the Journalism or the Economics Faculty
of the MSU and you study there for 5 years.
It's different here.
Precisely. And it's one of
the biggest differences
between Russian and American
education.
I enrolled in the Economics Faculty
of the MSU in the '90s.
I was 18.
I'm not sure that when you're 18,
you can tell with certainty
what you want to do
for the rest of your life,
biology, math, economy
and so on.
They have a different
approach here.
You're not enrolling
in a particular faculty.
They don't have faculties here.
You enroll in the Stanford University.
You do what you want
for the first two years.
Of course, there are limitations:
you have to take at least X courses,
you have to do Y amount of work.
You might get interested
in something along the way.
A ton of people start off on philosophy,
then switch to computer science,
or start off on physics,
then switch to biology, and so on.
Usually, only by your third year,
you're required to choose
a specialization.
But again, they call this
specialization "a major."
Major, greater.
It doesn't mean that
it's all you study.
It means that a set number
of your subjects
as well as your bachelor's thesis
will be on this subject.
There's a sister concept here in America
called "a minor," smaller.
Many students have
a major and a minor.
It means that you have
a primary specialization
and may have a secondary
specialization.
These two specializations
may be completely unrelated.
For example, you can have
Computer Science and Economics.
You can have
Physics and Music.
- You can have Engineering...
- ...and Marketing?
You can't get a bachelor's in Marketing,
there are limitations for specializations.
But, let's say, Engineering and Biology.
(title card music)
[*In Russian, "silikon" is both a transliteration]
[of the English name of the element Si (silicon)]
[and the correct name of the compound "silicone."]
[The proper name of the element in Russian is "kremniy."]
[A popular layman translation of the region's name]
[is therefore "Silicone Valley," if translated back to English.]
[The correct name "Kremniy Valley" has become]
[more popular in the recent years.]
Silikon or Kremniy* Valley?
I vote silikon. I'm actually against
silicone, but for it in this context.
But... Why? Kremniy is
the correct word, isn't it?
I'm used to it! I mean...
It sounds like Silicon Valley!
It doesn't matter. The Valley isn't
about tits OR silicon.
It's just a word.
I thought it was called
Silikon Valley as a kid.
I dreamed to go to Silikon,
ended up in Kremniy.
Why Kremniy?
The English word "silicon"
means "kremniy."
But somehow, someway,
half the Russians say "Silikon."
When you hear "Silikon,"
you know that it's wrong?
My inner Russian language A student says:
"Guys, it's fucking 'Kremniy!'"
But then my inner Marketing D student says:
"'Silikon' sounds way fucking cooler!"
(Dud' laughs)
"My inner A student."
Nice. Mine too gets me
into trouble all the time.
- The correct translation is "kremniy."
- Uh-huh?
"Silikon" is...
- Acceptable?
- Acceptable.
- Or is it hillbilly talk?
Hillbilly talk, yeah.
"Kremniy" of course.
Like the element.
So anyone who calls it "Silikon"
is a hillbilly?
Because it's not "silicon."
It's "kremniy."
What is "silikon?"
What's "silikon" in English?
It's just silicone.
The word "silikon" is a transliteration
of the English "silicon," i.e. "kremniy."
(title card music)
That's the main building
over there, right?
That one's the main building.
But yeah, this is all the main campus.
So this where it all... This was the first
building of Sergey Brin and friends?
Yeah. They originally had
an office in this building,
where all the big
discussions happened.
Where do you think is the office
where they bought YouTube?
I'm sure it was in Marrakesh,
in that building.
There's a huge conference room there
where they used to make all the decisions.
I recently remembered that...
I remember it like it happened yesterday.
I was working for the PROsport magazine.
One of my colleagues came in the room
and said: "They bought YouTube!"
(Doronichev laughs)
It's a historical deal!
They bought the company
for over a billion!
[In Fall of 2006, Google bought]
[YouTube for $1.65 billion]
They bought the company
for over a billion!
[In Fall of 2006, Google bought]
[YouTube for $1.65 billion]
Given that today, a billion is nothing for companies
like these, it sounds funny, doesn't it?
[In 2018, Morgan Stanley gave an estimate]
[that if YouTube was a separate company,]
[it would've been worth...]
We'll have a caption on screen with YouTube's
current estimated worth.
[In 2018, Morgan Stanley gave an estimate]
[that if YouTube was a separate company,]
[it would've been worth $160 billion]
I just can't recall from memory.
[In 2018, Morgan Stanley gave an estimate]
[that if YouTube was a separate company,]
[it would've been worth $160 billion]
It's billions and billions.
I've been in the Valley
for 5 years now.
Prior to that, I'd been communicating with
Americans via Skype and email for over 10 years.
So I initially understood
them through text.
I was an expert at typing
in English.
When I first came to the Valley,
I couldn't understand a word
besides "hello"
and "give me money."
Then you begin to understand that your
school and your university English
and California English
are completely different things.
Texas English is another
thing still.
When people tell you out here,
"Great! We love it! Fantastic!"
you can't Google-translate what they
actually mean — you have to sense it.
Read between the lines.
When I first came here,
I'd show my portfolio to everyone.
I was an okay artist.
Everyone said: "Great! Amazing!"
I figured I'd been underappreciated
back in Russia.
'Cause we, Russians, say:
"This is shit.
This one's a redo.
This one's... passable."
In America, they all said:
"Great! Amazing! We love you!"
I was like: "Shit! I'm staying!"
But then I noticed they said all the same
things to John from Alabama,
to Khan from India...
I went: "Crap! I must be doing
something wrong."
The Anglo-Saxon communication
culture is much more indirect.
We often step on...
Russian developers often
run into glass doors here
of what they consider hypocrisy.
That's not the case.
That's just local culture.
They believe here that telling someone
their work is bull is extremely rude.
It's worse than throwing
poop in someone's face.
It's better to throw poop in someone's
face than shit all over their work.
In Russia, it's normal.
They say: "Dude, what you're
doing is nonsense."
"It'll never take off.
This was a waste of time."
To us, that's normal.
But to Americans and the British,
that's extremely offensive.
So instead they'll tell you:
"This is amazing."
When you ask a Russian how's it going,
the typical response is: "It's going fine,"
which means it's going not bad,
it's good.
You don't say "good", because you
don't want them to think you're bragging.
Only to someone I'm truly close with, I could say:
"You know, things are actually going well!"
Or the opposite:
"Things are awful!"
Americans will tell everyone they're doing
"absolutely amazing."
Even if they have fresh bruises
on their face
from the worst possible morning
you could ever have,
they'll still say: "Amazing."
If they're not doing well,
they'll grumble: "Amazing."
Someone told us yesterday that they teach kids
storytelling here, from third or fifth grade.
- And kids in elementary school
can put together presentations.
- Yep.
Was that a lie?
That's actually true.
And in fact, that's another thing here
guys back at home could really use
to be successful in big
places like this one,
is the ability to communicate
effectively.
In Russia, and I know this from experience,
communication is much more direct,
and they find it really rough
and coarse here.
They don't try to smooth out
the edges.
They don't bother
with careful wording.
They just go: du-du-du-du!
They often end up unheard by folks here,
just because, woah!
I tried to figure out why that was the case.
In reality, they never teach us that.
They don't teach us in school
to present ourselves,
to effectively communicate
our ideas,
to debate with arguments
but politely.
They don't teach that.
You're good at dealing
with bullies outside.
You know your comebacks
to "whatcha lookin' at?"
But they don't teach you
how to pitch a startup idea.
I have a great example
from my own life.
I was very surprised. My daughter's been
going to school here since she was little.
I believe she was 8 or 9 at the time.
Eight.
She came home from school...
I had no idea she could do
anything on the computer.
She came home from school and said: "Parents,
I need you to plug the computer in the big screen."
"I made a presentation."
We were like: "What?
What presentation?"
She plugs the computer in.
She made slides.
She has a perfectly structured,
clearly technique-driven pitch
on the subject:
"We need a cat."
She starts going:
"Here's a set of issues. I'm cold and lonely
in bed at night, so I don't sleep well."
"And I don't study well."
"We need a cat."
"If we get a cat, I'll learn to be responsible
and take care of this small creature."
"Du-du-du-du-du."
So she pitched me a cat
in five minutes.
- I was super against pets.
- So insidious!
And now I have a cat! (laughs)
After I landed at the San Francisco
airport,
my partner and I went
to rent a car.
We came to this booth,
where the salesman told us
about the insurance,
how much it's gonna cost,
and so on and so forth.
And he said: "What do you do?
Why did you come?"
We said we were programmers
from Belarus
and we came to show
our startup to the world. So...
He went: "Guys! You're programmers, huh?
I have this crazy idea..."
He starts talking about his super idea.
"Pitching" it, as they call it.
He's pitching his startup.
We're in shock!
If some small car rental salesman
is carrying around a startup idea
and tries to pitch it,
then, damn, this place
is truly full of
ideas, active people and dreamers.
To stay as up to date as possible, you need
to maintain social connections and network
with everyone.
So far, this is one of our biggest
impressions from the Valley:
even waiting in a restaurant line,
for a table to free up,
they start talking to each other,
knowing that this waiting-in-line
small talk
could help them out in the future.
It could help with networking.
But it's so cynical!
Well, small talk is a cultural thing.
It's not about getting something out of it.
They're not trying to hook you.
But you're right, people here are always
trying to meet someone useful.
Isn't it cynical?
I don't find it cynical,
because everyone everywhere
needs something from others.
You can try and meet
people in Moscow
because you wanna get
a contract with them
or you're hoping for a recommendation
or a promotion.
Down here, they're just
upfront about it.
It takes a lot more time and effort to move this
relationship along here than it is in Moscow.
In Moscow, you can meet with someone over coffee,
talk with them for 40 minutes and sign a contract.
Or agree to sign a contract
after one dinner.
I'm sure many have.
Down here, in most cases,
it takes, like, five years
of being in the same environment, being around,
taking your kids to the same school,
playing at the same golf club,
going to the same pottery class,
whatever,
and only then you go:
"Hey, John, so what do you do again?"
- Though you know exactly what they do?
- Of course.
Ugh!
There's something called
UberPool.
You call a taxi,
but you don't ride alone —
you pick someone up along the way
and you split the cost of the ride.
Say, if a normal Uber ride costs $10,
an UberPool ride costs $5.
- He just picks people up?
- Yeah. Along the way.
It takes longer, it's inconvenient,
there's someone else in the car and so on.
Anyway, I called an UberPool.
We were scraping by at the time.
I paid the $5. We picked up
another dude.
He also called an UberPool.
We start talking.
"What do you do?"
"I'm an entrepreneur."
We're both entrepreneurs.
Ten minutes later, we're making
plans for world domination.
...When neither of us can pay
for a solo taxi ride.
- Did the driver turn around
and offer funding?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
He offered to drive us for free.
- So everyone's obsessed with it?
- Yeah.
It's like Hollywood
for the entertainment industry.
But it's, like, painful?
- Painful how?
- That everyone's obsessed.
Yes and no. This kind of
concentration of unified context
makes people think
in one direction.
That's what produces these
cutting-edge ideas.
Thanks to this context, everyone's
thinking about it all the time.
You walk around and you can't
not think about it.
That's why I think you get
these cutting-edge ideas.
That's why the Valley is so great
and performs so...
That's why you can't
replicate the Valley.
You can't replicate such
density of context.
A week in these cafés
is worth much more
than a month or a year at
Four Seasons Moscow in coffee,
because you soak it all in here.
How does it work?
You sit at a table at that
pancake place over there.
And what? Someone useful
can walk in?
There's 74,000 people living in Palo Alto.
About half of them are in IT.
On our way here,
half of the people in that Starbucks
work at Google, LinkedIn, Facebook.
They connect very easily.
We have a friend who used to work
as a barista at a Starbucks,
but had an idea for a startup.
Where did he meet
his first investor?
In that very Starbucks.
Some guy from Google just
walked in to get a coffee.
Vanilla-cappuccino 2-in-1.
And signed him a check
for $100,000.
That's a small sum, right?
It's a tiny sum, yeah.
I think he lended him
some of his pocket money,
his bonus for that month.
Did the startup take off?
Honestly! Be honest now!
We did a number of projects. Some of them
worked out, some of them didn't.
Did the Starbucks guy's project
take off?
We're currently working
with him, yes.
- Oh! As..?
- He just got initial funding from...
- You work as an investor?
- As partners.
We're doing visual graphics for him.
What's the startup for?
Video games?
AI.
This place attracts
the most ambitious,
the most passionate, the people that want
to change the world or the humanity.
Whenever you move up one step, there's always
someone one step above to compare yourself to.
You exist in this progression.
You're surrounded by people who...
You might say: "My company's worth
tens of millions of dollars."
Someone turns around and says:
"Mine's worth hundreds of millions."
And you're, like, okay,
we've got work to do.
You get constant reminders that
you can do better, faster, stronger.
You come to a party,
you meet people...
There's some guy,
you shake his hand,
and he might say:
"We raised 20 million yesterday."
You're like:
"Okay, I'm outta here."
That's normal.
Something I noticed
working with Google,
these days, instead of hiring
people with one success
they hire those with five failures.
'Cause these people know
what they did wrong.
If they can analyze and process it,
next time, they'll act differently.
This is a new trend in the Valley.
People care about
failed projects,
and if you've analyzed it,
they'll want to support you.
'Cause you want risk-takers now.
Everything's been done. You can use templates
to make a typical game or a typical film.
People don't get hyped for those.
You have to think outside the box.
How? By trial and error.
You mean someone with two failed projects is more
useful than someone with three successes?
Five failures are better
than one success.
With three successes, you're probably
on par with Google yourself
and you can invest in new
startups yourself.
Another important thing
is tolerance to failure.
Meaning, failing in the Valley
is not shameful.
So for example, I'm checking out
résumés,
and someone comes to an interview and says,
"My startup failed, so I'm looking for a job,"
or, "I've had two major failures."
I don't think to myself:
"Why would I hire you then?"
I think that this person...
They have experienced failure and are therefore
more valuable than someone who hasn't.
- So he's not a loser, he's a guy with experience?
- He's a guy with experience.
And also he's proven that he can get up
after a failure and move forward.
That's super important, because given
what this place is all about,
failing is pretty much a mandatory
part of the game.
You're constantly failing because you're
trying out new and crazy ideas all the time.
If you're not failing, then you're not
taking enough risks.
That's super important.
And the final thing that,
in my opinion,
has a big effect on local business
and the community itself
is the acceptance and tolerance
towards the crazy, the unconventional,
the things you're not used to —
all this wacky stuff.
'Cause all great ideas
sound crazy at first.
If you can't accept people
that dress differently,
or act differently,
or something like that,
a community like that probably won't
support a crazy new idea like:
"Hey, let's make a social network
"where people will use their real
names and share pictures?"
When Facebook was just starting,
this idea sounded crazy.
No one used their real names
on the internet.
But venture capitalists believe
in those ideas and offer funding
because it's common knowledge here
that crazy ideas are a good thing.
And they know that they can fail.
Are there as many broken dreams
as in La La Land?
When you move here to become a star of the industry
but end up making coffee at a Starbucks.
Yes.
This is what I talked about
at the start.
Unlike La La Land, where your success depended
on the backup of producers and studios...
You didn't have YouTube
to put together a team
and start filming interviews
and become a star.
They didn't have that in Hollywood.
Well, unlike that scenario,
here, you've always had it.
You come here alone.
You rent a garage.
Or you don't even rent a garage
and just sit at home
like these guys
and you work on your idea
until it become something big.
You're the master
of your fate here.
That's the biggest difference
with Hollywood.
(title card music)
(voices, car engine, street sounds)
I was in shock at first.
My friend and I, we used to smoke
cigarettes back then,
left our apartment...
Smoking cigarettes is extremely
unpopular here.
If you're standing with a cigarette outside,
people will recoil from you,
like you're shooting up heroine
in the middle of the street.
It's that strong.
So we're standing there smoking,
and a police car pulls up.
This huge SUV, bunch of lights.
The cop's a Navy SEAL: bulletproof vest,
tattoos — scary stuff.
He turns to us and says:
"How's it going?"
We drop the cigarettes and go:
"We good! We good!
We don't want any trouble!"
"There are 'no smoking' signs that way and
that way. We thought we'd smoke here."
He's goes: "Guys... I just asked
how you were doing."
We're like: "We're doing fine. Why?"
"Great. I just wanted to remind you
that there's no crosswalk here."
"So when you go back across, please,
make sure a car doesn't hit you."
"This is a dangerous stretch.
Please, be careful."
Salutes us and leaves.
We stood there in silence for, like, five minutes,
trying to process what just happened.
(laughs) "Why did he pull up?"
"He was going on his business, noticed we were
standing somewhere we could get hit,
"told us to be careful crossing
the road and left?"
[*Protagonist of a series of Soviet poems for children,]
[an exemplary citizen that helped others in need.]
[The author eventually turned him into a police officer]
[that continued doing good deeds above and beyond]
[his regular duties.]
"Is he a real-life Uncle Stiopa*?"
Turned out, yeah. Down here, a police
officer is a respected job.
They salute the police.
They love 'em.
If you wanna get any sort of
professional help here,
you should expect
that it's gonna cost you.
Even supposedly menial jobs
like waste collectors, plumbers
or gardeners.
Gardeners charge $200 for a visit.
- The place will get overgrown without them?
- Yeah.
It IS overgrown, actually.
The landlord doesn't hire help.
These are all weeds.
[*In Russian, the word sounds Medieval,]
[and thus humorous.]
(chuckles) "Landlord!*"
- So okay. You have two kids, right?
- Yes.
How much money do you need here
to support a family of four
without shelling out like a rapper?
Twenty.
- Twenty thousand bucks, if you don't go crazy.
- Yeah.
Thirty, if you spend freely?
Yeah.
Damn.
Depends on your definition
of "freely."
If you make $50,000 a month, that means
you get $30,000 post-tax?
- More like $25,000.
- Got it.
- So for a decent living, you have to make
at least $500,000 a year?
- Yeah.
- From two salaries.
- Damn.
- Do Facebook engineers make
that kind of money?
- Yes.
- A typical engineer?
- Well, a typical engineer makes
around $250,000 a year.
I.e. twenty-ish a month.
But that's a tenner post-tax?
You spend those on housing,
taxes and, say, food,
but you also get options
and bonuses.
[Options are company shares given to employees]
[to motivate and keep them from leaving;]
[paid out separately from normal salary]
They're automatically put
in you savings account.
[Options are company shares given to employees]
[to motivate and keep them from leaving;]
[paid out separately from normal salary]
There's also a separate
pension savings account.
[Options are company shares given to employees]
[to motivate and keep them from leaving;]
[paid out separately from normal salary]
So in total, a Facebook engineer
could make a million a year.
But they'll still only get
about $300,000 in cash.
How much do programmers
make in the Valley?
It depends, but programmers do have
really big salaries here.
That's because competition
is mostly for talent
rather than markets
and whatever else.
Or users.
By 'talent' I mean any kind of
professional.
The starting salary of a software engineer
who's just graduated college
is around $120,000,
something like that.
- A year?
- Yes. And from there...
- Important note: 120 is pre-tax, right?
- Yes.
Post-tax, that's 60?
With $120,000, they probably get
$80 to 90 thousand,
'cause it's a progressive tax scale.
It starts from 30%.
What if you're coming in from Russia
and already have experience?
Then it's $200 to 300 thousand.
And once you start producing results...
It all depends on your performance.
Down here, no one really cares
about your titles or credentials,
or your accolades or whatever.
If you don't produce quality work,
you won't be making any money.
If you do produce quality work, no one will care
that you don't have a diploma.
You'll make half a million,
a million and so on.
What are the housing prices?
I used to rent a small room
for $3000.
The best part about it was...
- Room or apartment?
- A room.
- But it was right next to Google.
- But you had roommates?
- Yeah, I did.
I know you can rent a decent
house for $5000 to $7000.
But it's something a ways.
In the center, it's 10k and up.
That's just rent.
- What about buying?
- Five to ten million dollars.
[*~1300 square feet.]
- For a 120-meter* shack?
- For a fixer-upper, yeah. Something pretty
from the get-go will cost more.
120 meters, cardboard walls, three meters away
from the next house — this could cost 5 million?
...small lawn. Yeah.
Most of the people doing well here
are the IT crowd.
Half of the menial workers
live below the poverty line.
It's the other side of the Valley.
Palo Alto was a small town
just 30 years ago.
If you watch James Franco's movie.
He was born here.
He made a film about the Palo Alto
of his childhood.
It's a typical small town
where IT took off, is all.
The IT crowd used to comprise
10% of the population. Now, it's 50%.
The rest aren't doing as well.
How is it possible that over here,
houses cost millions of dollars,
cross the road,
and it's a total A?
I still can't wrap my head around
this side of America.
It's not just this place. You walk down
the street in LA, it's all classy and fancy,
cross the road, it's homeless people, crazies,
and someone's pointing a gun at you.
You walk five meters back,
and it's scents and corgis.
That's because...
(both laugh)
Because what?
It's because municipalities get financing
from their respective neighborhoods.
Palo Alto is where the IT crowd lives.
They can pay for the police and the firemen.
Happy firemen.
East Palo Alto doesn't have IT.
They have a lot of crime. So they
can't fund police or medicine.
- But they're neighborhoods of the same city!
- They get funding separately, each has its own.
That's why it's hard to imagine
this in Moscow:
you can go here, but you never
go there, even in broad daylight.
Yeah, Moscow doesn't
have ghettos.
Yeah. In San Francisco,
even Americans say:
"Stay away from that place.
Always."
Until very recently, East Palo Alto
was the "murder capital" of the US.
Beating New York and such.
They were the first city in the US to use
the automatic police alert system
with gunshot sound
triangulation.
You shoot a gun, and there's
a police car on its way.
If you wanna call the cops
in East Palo Alto,
because you're being mugged or something,
shoot in the air or the mugger.
It instantly calls a car?
Wait, there are mics in the air?
It's a audio system that triangulates your
location based on the gunshot sound.
- Holy crap.
- I don't know if they're still using it,
but they used to.
- But you cross the road, and there's
Apple's HQ.
- Across the road. Yeah.
Well, Apple's in Cupertino.
But Facebook's here. Yeah.
You cross the road,
and there's Facebook's HQ.
Facebook, Stanford.
The poverty threshold here
is $200,000.
So if you're someone who makes
less than $200,000...
- A year?
- A year.
Wait, let's break it down for clarity.
- If you make less than $17,500
a month...
- A month.
If my math's correct.
[His math was wrong:]
[$200,000 a year = $16,666 a month]
- Approximately.
- Give or take, yeah.
[His math was wrong:]
[$200,000 a year = $16,666 a month]
...you're poor?
[His math was wrong:]
[$200,000 a year = $16,666 a month]
Not just poor. You need
to be subsidized.
[His math was wrong:]
[$200,000 a year = $16,666 a month]
- If you make less than 17,5k..?
- Yes.
But it makes sense, because...
First, we're not taking into account how much
of that you're giving up in taxes.
There are federal taxes. According
to them, it's a large sum.
You pay a large a tax from it.
Super expensive housing,
ridiculous healthcare.
I don't get sick a lot.
I have great health.
But I still spend $20,000
a year on healthcare.
On health insurance?
Yeah. Insurance combined with some
minor things. Totals at 20k.
You ever filled a cavity
in the Valley?
No. I do full-body maintenance in Russia
whenever I get the chance.
'Cause it's also faster.
Importantly, in Russia, it's not just
cheaper; it's better.
When you come to a doctor
in the US,
you spend an hour in line,
even though you pay $1000 for it.
Narking is another thing here.
- They do that here?
- Of course they do.
It's not just there. It's great!
When you first come here, you're like:
"What? How can you nark out your neighbor?"
But then you realize that it's
super convenient.
Let's say, I'm pissed that my neighbor leaves his trash bins out in a way
that they stink up the place
where I cook barbecue.
Right?
I can tell he's violating
some regulations.
What are my options? I can
come up to him and go:
"Hey, buddy, could move your bins?"
He'll tell me: "Screw you."
We'll get in a fist fight.
At best, we'll have an argument
and harass each other for a while.
Instead, I can call the sheriff
and go:
"Sheriff, bro, my neighbor's stinking my place up
with his trash bins. Could you take care of it?"
The sheriff goes to him and says: "Dude,
move your trash bins or next time I'll fine you."
- Problem solved. You have a wonderful
moderator.
- You ever did that?
No. But I plan on narking one
of my neighbors out.
- You're okay with it?
- Perfectly okay.
That's something you grow into. First, you need
to learn to trust the sheriff as your friend
and realize that this dude doesn't
expect you to bribe him.
That's difficult, you agree?
It's very difficult!
One of my first trips was...
I really wanted to do this, I did some
research and found Jobs' houses.
Jobs' old houses.
Jobs' current houses.
The reason this was so
illuminating was that...
Sadly, this was right after
Jobs had passed away.
[Steve Jobs died in 2011]
I come to this house.
First thing that struck was, rather than
a house of glass and concrete,
[Steve Jobs died in 2011]
this was more like
a hobbit's cottage.
A really conservative little old house.
You may know that his car of choice
was Mercedes 500SL.
And he'd always get a new one to avoid
putting number plates on it.
Drove around without plates.
Parked in handicapped spaces.
Whenever it was time to install
the number plates,
in six or twelve months,
I can't remember exactly,
instead of installing them,
he'd return the car to the dealership,
the dealership would sell it
as Jobs' ex-car
and give Jobs a new Mercedes.
The fact that it was a hobbit's cottage
rather than a glass-and-concrete house,
was that a quirk of his mentality
or classic IT guy psyche?
Lack of time?
Exactly. It was good enough.
That's like his 50 black turtlenecks.
Another one of his houses,
the one he grew up in,
his parents' house,
was also this tiny little house
with a garage where it all started.
That's the most fascinating thing in the Valley to me —
going to these places where you see
this plain house and this plain garage,
where they started.
They didn't come up with any intermediate
steps before they'd get to work.
They didn't think, "Oh, I need to raise funds first,"
or, "I need to get this extra degree."
They sat down in their garage and started working
because they were excited about it there and then.
I believe that that's how great
companies are created.
It's exciting to witness that.
Someone told us you could meet Sergey Brin
out in the city alone, without security.
Yeah, he took his kids to our
school for two years.
Then their mom said the school had weak math
and transferred them to a different one.
The only security he had was this
60-ish-year-old guy
in a white Prius,
that always slept, or pretended to sleep,
in the parking lot,
and some suspicious gardeners would walk around
in the forest, doing... something... in the forest.
- You think it was his security?
- It was definitely his security.
Because as soon as they
transferred their kids,
both the gardeners and the guy
in the white car disappeared.
They do it carefully.
- Discreetly?
- Super discreetly!
Unless you specifically
look for them
and go: "Uh-huh! This guy's new!"
every day,
you'll never notice them.
Zuckerberg has a lot more security.
They, like, put him in a van.
There's another van
following his van.
He has sort of presidential ambitions
in terms of security.
Whereas Brin and Page...
Tim Cook goes to my gym.
[Tim Cook is the CEO of Apple]
Only he goes there at 5 AM
to avoid being bugged.
[Tim Cook is the CEO of Apple]
- With pitches? With startup offers?
- Yeah.
[Tim Cook is the CEO of Apple]
Which is weird, right?
On the show Billions, New York traders
make fun of each other, going:
"Wait, you go to a gym
with other people in it?"
"Are you poor or something?"
Whereas Tim Cook, the CEO of Apple,
mind you, goes to Equinox
that charges $100 a month
and anyone can afford it.
Why does he go there?
It's convenient and comfortable for him.
Why should he do anything special?
They don't appreciate
showoffs here.
I have lots of neighbors that make
a lot more money than me,
but they all drive regular cars
and wear regular clothes.
Showing off your wealth is
frowned upon in the Valley.
They'll point fingers at you and go:
"Ugh! Showoff."
- This is a fairly well-off neighborhood.
- Yeah.
Mildly speaking.
But when it comes to fences...
I can see a small picket
fence over there,
but they don't put up tall
ones here, do they?
Yeah, it's actually prohibited.
It was a tradition at first, but when Russians
started coming in, they passed a law.
First, the are wild deer.
Tall fences disturb them.
Second, they make your neighbors
uncomfortable.
Everyone has to maintain an open path
through their land here.
The law requires that you have
a path for horseback riders.
You gotta spend your own money to build
a special path that meets certain guidelines
that's comfortable for horsies
to hoof along.
If you do a poor job maintaining it,
your neighbors will nark you out:
"We maintain our side of the path.
This asshole doesn't. Please, fine him."
The Valley has an insane
shortage of girls.
The ratio is something
like 70 to 30.
- Around 70.
- For real?
How do guys live here?
This joke from Silicon Valley:
"It was a great party last night.
There were eight girls at once!"
(Miheyenko laughs)
So that's pretty much real?
[*Saint Petersburg.]
It is close to real. It was a bit of a shock
for me too after Moscow and Peter*.
When you're used to Russian
beautie...ful sights,
you move here and you're super confused,
like: where are they?
Are they hiding them from you?
What's going on?
How do you meet girls over here?
I understand they're a minority here?
So I'm not an expert.
I'm desperately married.
But my friends complain to me
about that all the time.
They say: "That's it. I'm done.
I'm booking a flight to Odessa."
I'm like: "What? What flight?
We have a ton of work to do!"
He goes: "I can't take this anymore.
I'm going to Odessa. Give me one week."
(laughs) I... I...
I go, "What happened?"
He says, "Let me show you
my Tinder."
He starts swiping through Tinder,
and yeah,
if I was looking for someone
to try and start a relationship,
I doubt I would use
Tinder for that,
but if I did, I would spend
A LOT of time swiping.
There are just few women here
demographically.
Ever since the gold rush, right?
Yeah. No one knows how many
arrived by land.
They only registered those
that arrived by sea.
In '49, 70 thousand people arrived.
Only a thousand of them were women.
[He's talking about 1849]
In '49, 70 thousand people arrived.
Only a thousand of them were women.
- That's...
- One to seventy.
One to seventy!
And they were someone's wives.
(laughs)
There were no free women.
That's why all the way back in 1849, they had
an actual gay neighborhood in San Francisco.
The American LGBT community has been
drawn to this place ever since,
because 'queer' has been
normal for so long here.
So the only practical option
is bringing along a wife?
Yeah.
Or occasionally go: "I can't take this
anymore! I'm going to Odessa!"
[*Capitals of Belarus, Russia and Ukraine.]
[The implication is that the "unwind city"]
[will depend on the country you came from.]
Or Minsk, or Moscow, or Kiev*.
I moved with my lady.
We later broke up.
My current girlfriend is...
Well, she's Russian too.
It's an issue.
It's a big issue here.
But on the bright side,
nothing's distracting you
from work.
Not even nocturnal emissions?
Yeah. At some point,
it all just stops.
You wake up and all you think about
is ploughing on.
(title card music)
- Hey, I saw birches over there.
- Yeah!
Birches are everywhere, dude.
Every country I lived in, I've lived in five,
I had a birch tree next to my house.
[*Diminutive of berioza, "birch tree."]
Why did they tell me in school that a beriozka*
could only grow on Russian soil?
Because a beriozka is
a metaphysical concept.
You do miss the beriozka birches when you're anywhere but in Russia.
You wanna be careful with them. You come to Russia,
those beriozkas, they pull you in and don't let go.
Dude, stop torturing me!
(Doronichev laughs)
So it's another school
myth then?
Yeah, it's a very common plant.
Birch tree.
(Dud') No one identifies it
with Russia?
(Doronichev) Well, you and I do.
- (Dud') But Americans wouldn't
understand why we..?
- No, they wouldn't.
It's like if you monopolized the palm tree
and started telling everyone that palm trees
were inherently Russian.
Very few people intentionally
create bubbles.
A lot of the time,
they happen on their own.
- For example?
- Usually, they're created by investors.
- Is there a textbook example of a bubble?
- Theranos.
They made a book about it...
"Made a book?"
Made a movie, wrote a book.
The investigation.
Founder's being sued.
Elizabeth Holmes,
a blonde in a turtleneck
like Jobs'
with intense grey eyes
and an unnaturally
low-pitched voice,
was obsessed with the idea that huge
machines for blood testing were stupid
and we needed something that would let
anyone donate a little blood at home
to do 150 different tests.
Parading this vision,
she collected investor money.
She managed to lure in
some incredible talent.
She had a seriously
impressive team.
She'd sign hundred-million-dollar
contracts with pharmacy chains
who'd say: "Here, we're happy to pay
for your machines in advance."
Something like nine years later, she's got nada:
no machines, no technology, nothing.
The company's worth $9 billion.
She's worth $4.5 billion.
[In 2015, Forbes named then 31-year-old Holmes]
[the youngest and wealthiest female billionaire in the US.]
[Several months later, The Wall Street Journal released]
[an investigation that brought about the exposure of]
[Theranos. Forbes subsequently revised Holmes' net worth]
[to be zero. Theranos shut down in 2018. As of spring of]
[2020, Holmes is charged with 11 counts of wire fraud,]
[court hearing pending. She is facing 20 years in prison]
In real money?
[In 2015, Forbes named then 31-year-old Holmes]
[the youngest and wealthiest female billionaire in the US.]
[Several months later, The Wall Street Journal released]
[an investigation that brought about the exposure of]
[Theranos. Forbes subsequently revised Holmes' net worth]
[to be zero. Theranos shut down in 2018. As of spring of]
[2020, Holmes is charged with 11 counts of wire fraud,]
[court hearing pending. She is facing 20 years in prison]
Well, she cashed in some
of the money, yeah.
[In 2015, Forbes named then 31-year-old Holmes]
[the youngest and wealthiest female billionaire in the US.]
[Several months later, The Wall Street Journal released]
[an investigation that brought about the exposure of]
[Theranos. Forbes subsequently revised Holmes' net worth]
[to be zero. Theranos shut down in 2018. As of spring of]
[2020, Holmes is charged with 11 counts of wire fraud,]
[court hearing pending. She is facing 20 years in prison]
This was a textbook bubble.
[In 2015, Forbes named then 31-year-old Holmes]
[the youngest and wealthiest female billionaire in the US.]
[Several months later, The Wall Street Journal released]
[an investigation that brought about the exposure of]
[Theranos. Forbes subsequently revised Holmes' net worth]
[to be zero. Theranos shut down in 2018. As of spring of]
[2020, Holmes is charged with 11 counts of wire fraud,]
[court hearing pending. She is facing 20 years in prison]
She was blowing it up
in hopes that...
There's an expression in the Valley,
"fake it till you make it."
"Pretend until you actually do it."
Is Tesla a bubble?
Tesla has a product, it has customers,
it has an army of fans.
It's sold hundreds of
thousands of cars.
What about the share sales?
Aren't they essentially donations?
They're not exactly donations.
Tesla has awful financial management.
Just awful.
In terms of financial management,
Tesla operates like a small startup,
even though it's a huge
car manufacturer.
That's inexcusable irresponsibility.
The company's bank account has enough
money to last it just three or four months.
That's an indefensible level of risk
for such a company.
At the same time, they have
a fairly reliable product.
They have a huge international
network of charging stations.
I mean, the product's cool, right?
- Someone will buy Tesla if they start to...
- The Chinese?
- China's out.
- Why?
Big politics got involved.
Trump's grabbed hold of the Valley
and all this stuff, and charged the...
There's this committee called CFIUS.
It's a trade commission that decides
which export deals are okay
and which aren't.
They recently said that, in addition to the defense
industry, the state should also oversee IT.
If you're an American company
that develops AI technology,
like autopilots or whatever
with potential for military use,
they will have to approve the sale of your
company and even your stock.
That's why local Chinese venture funds
are closing one after the other.
- Stas! You work for Tesla.
- Yes.
[STANISLAV YERIOMIN]
[31 years old]
- Stas! You work for Tesla.
- Yes.
[STANISLAV YERIOMIN]
[31 years old]
- As an engineer.
- No.
[STANISLAV YERIOMIN]
[Works for Tesla]
- As an engineer.
- No.
[STANISLAV YERIOMIN]
[Works for Tesla]
- What then?
- Engineering manager.
[STANISLAV YERIOMIN]
[Works for Tesla]
- You supervise engineers.
- More or less.
In plain terms,
your army of engineers stuffs this beauty
with all the features that we know of.
In fact, my army is responsible for
everything starting and running
properly on this thing.
All of the software in this car.
Damn!
We're touching the future right now,
aren't we? Or rather the present.
Actually, for me, this is the past. (laughs)
'Cause I first saw the current firmware
about six months ago.
Right?
'Cause we constantly update it
and add new features
and new cool things and roll them out
for users all over the world.
You can't see this,
but I basically have this
huge tablet over here.
And... What is it showing?
Actually, it's showing that we're on Mars
and providing navigation on Mars.
It's one of the car's Easter eggs,
to show that you're on Mars.
- This is an actual map of Mars.
- Why? What's the idea?
It's a reference to SpaceX.
If we go to About This Car,
it will show the properties
of one of SpaceX's
ships.
(Yeriomin) How about we get
warm and comfy?
(silence)
(whirring, sound of fireplace)
(Dud') Damn!
It's like those big-screen
fireplaces they hang in offices.
(Yeriomin) Know what's missing?
The smell of burning wood.
Would've been better.
(Dud') The sound!
- (Dud') The sound!!
- Yeah, it does sound good. (laughs)
(Dud') Anyone ever complained they
thought their car was on fire?
(music starts playing)
(Dud') Damn!
- Are those vegetable patches?
- They are! For gardeners.
That's normal here.
Say, you're a gardener,
you wanna dig around in dirt a little
and grow something to unwind.
You go outside and garden.
- Some employee enjoys gardening...
- Yeah.
They have some gardening patches out here
and they come out on breaks to...
(Doronichev) ...to grow some cabbages.
Have you seen Elon Musk?
I sit pretty close to him.
I see him every Tuesday.
- He sits out with everyone?
- Yeah.
Well, not exactly out.
- There's the office floor, and then a small room,
it's open too.
- Yeah?
And his open office
is in that room.
And like all the local billionaires,
he's super chill and works
next to everyone?
Yep. Yep.
He walks around.
He talks to people.
I first met him in my first
week on the job.
I didn't know if he was
around or whatever.
I come out of the, excuse the details,
bathroom,
staring at my phone, typing,
talking to someone.
Someone walks past me
and goes: "Hey! Hi."
That's a standard American greeting even
for people you don't necessarily know.
I was already used to it.
I went, "Hi."
Without even looking up. And I sensed something's
wrong because people started turning heads.
People still turn their heads
when he walks past.
I looked up. It was Elon.
- A real live Musk?!
- Yep. The real deal.
(car beeps)
(car buzzes three times)
(muffled Wizards in Winter by Trans-Siberian
Orchestra starts playing)
That's another mode.
(music continues playing)
What is it doing?
That's the Christmas Mode.
It's presenting itself or something?
Something like that, yeah.
- "Come here, driver."
- You could say that.
- Woah!
- It's starting.
- Damn!
(music gets louder and continues playing)
(lights flash in sync with guitars and keyboards)
(Dud') That's crazy!
Look, it's flapping its wings.
- (Dud') I understand that it's like car striptease?
- Sort of.
(Dud') It's like she's undressing so you...
(Yeriomin) Yeah. For your visual pleasure.
I'm not leaving my baby. I'm not!
Despite this undressing act!
(Yeriomin) So tempting.
She's tempting you
with those open doors.
(music reaches crescendo and ends)
Holy shit!
(title card music)
(Davidov) Over there is Cupertino, which you probably
know by the "designed in California" guys.
- (Dud') That's the site of Apple's presentations.
- Yeah.
Behind Cupertino is Milpitas
and other small villages.
That way's Mountain View,
home of Google.
Those two large hangars are where
NASA used to build blimps.
Google's leasing them now.
They leased that place for 50 years
because it has an airfield for jets.
[Moffett Federal Airfield]
'Cause Google's execs
fly on private jets.
[Moffett Federal Airfield]
And not just Google's execs.
Also at this Moffett Airfield,
the place with the hangars,
Yuriy Milner hosts his own Nobel Prize
called the Breakthrough Awards.
[Yuriy Milner is the founder of DST Global investment group.]
[Some of his investees include VK, Facebook, Twitter,]
[Alibaba Group, Xiaomi, Spotify, Airbnb and others]
Yuriy Milner hosts his own Nobel Prize
called the Breakthrough Awards.
[Yuriy Milner is the founder of DST Global investment group.]
[Some of his investees include VK, Facebook, Twitter,]
[Alibaba Group, Xiaomi, Spotify, Airbnb and others]
He organized his own Nobel Prize.
[Yuriy Milner is the founder of DST Global investment group.]
[Some of his investees include VK, Facebook, Twitter,]
[Alibaba Group, Xiaomi, Spotify, Airbnb and others]
He figured the Nobel Prize sucked
because it's awarded to old people
for things they did ages ago, and it's all outdated,
and the discipline list is outdated.
And the prize is too small.
Let's award more money for pioneering
achievements here and now.
[Breakthrough Prize winners receive $3,000,000.]
[A Nobel Prize in 2019 awarded $1,100,000]
Let's award more money for pioneering
achievements here and now.
[Breakthrough Prize winners receive $3,000,000.]
[A Nobel Prize in 2019 awarded $1,100,000]
They organized a really cool prize.
[Breakthrough Prize winners receive $3,000,000.]
[A Nobel Prize in 2019 awarded $1,100,000]
Hosts include Zuckerberg,
Milner himself, Musk.
What's your take on Yuriy Milner?
I think we should be proud
of Yuriy Milner.
He's a true...
He's probably the only Russian name
in the Valley's investment circles
that's precisely on the same level
as all the other local
Silicon Valley VCs,
venture capitalists.
The deals he's made and the outcomes
of those deals,
including investing in VK,
they're brilliant,
well thought-out moves
that, from the top of my head, none of the other
Russian investors have made.
Same with Facebook, in which
he invested very early on.
Milner is like an apostle
of venture capital.
Milner is great in that he's
the first Russian investor
who made a fortune
using venture capital
and proved to the world that Russia
has both money and the brains
to manage this money wisely,
and also entrepreneurs
to capitalize on.
But the bulk of his investments
weren't in Russian business?
Later on, no, but he started
with Russian business.
His main asset was Mail.Ru,
which he basically collected piece
by piece and took it public.
Later on, when they were going public,
he invested in Facebook,
he invested in Twitter, he invested
in Groupon, Zynga...
The list of companies he and his fund DST
have invested in goes on and on.
He's probably one of two or three
people in the Valley
responsible for the idea
of the unicorn race.
A unicorn is a company that costs one billion
dollars, yep, and is still privately owned.
It hasn't gone public.
The reasoning used to be:
"I'll create a company. Let it grow."
"Once it's worth $1 billion, I'll go to the stock market.
From then on, we'll be a public company."
"We'll issue new shares. Investors at
the stock market will buy them."
"That's how we grow. We'll know
exactly how much we're worth."
Milner said: "Uh-uh."
"We can raise enough money
"to go public when the company's worth
$100 billion rather than $1 billion."
In the movie Social Network, Sean Parker
tells the young Zuckerberg:
"A million dollars isn't cool.
A billion dollars is."
Then Milner comes along and says:
"Dude, a billion dollars isn't cool.
A hundred billions are."
Milner is in the movie?
No, he isn't. But he would've
been in the sequel.
Because Milner came to Facebook
and didn't just beat
all other offers.
Everyone here was doing
the cuckoo sign at first:
some crazy Russian showed up and bought
the most expensive house in the Valley.
Something like $120 or $140 million.
[According to Wall Street Journal, in 2011, Milner bought]
[a house in the Silicon Valley for $100 million]
OUCH! (coughs)
[According to Wall Street Journal, in 2011, Milner bought]
[a house in the Silicon Valley for $100 million]
The most expensive house
ever sold in the Valley.
[According to Wall Street Journal, in 2011, Milner bought]
[a house in the Silicon Valley for $100 million]
- Fence?
- No. No fence.
Well, a chain-link one.
Then he comes to Facebook who are unable
to raise more money than in the previous round.
I believe they'd gotten $6 billion.
Now, they were being offered $4 billion.
Milner shows up and says:
"Guys, I'll give you ten."
"I can also tell you're having
trouble raising money."
"I'll be your agent. I'll help you raise
money in all future rounds."
As an adviser?
Yeah. He lead them all the way
to IPO on NASDAQ,
where they were worth $70 billion,
I believe, at the time of offering.
Today, they're worth $400 to $500
depending on stock price.
How much did he multiply
his investment?
Uh... Seven times. At least.
In the process, he made money
off of WhatsApp.
'Cause Facebook bought WhatsApp with
a substantial amount of their shares.
[Facebook bought WhatsApp in 2014 for $19 billion.]
[A substantial portion of this sum was paid]
[with Facebook shares]
'Cause Facebook bought WhatsApp with
a substantial amount of their shares.
[Facebook bought WhatsApp in 2014 for $19 billion.]
[A substantial portion of this sum was paid]
[with Facebook shares]
Milner was an early investor
of WhatsApp too.
Do you think it's a team?
I mean, he manages a fund where a team
of people predicts where to invest.
He has intuition and great
understanding of the market.
'Cause the most important thing here today
is predicting what's gonna happen tomorrow.
Today, AI and biomedicine are king.
Virtual reality, which was popular three
years ago, has fallen off considerably.
It's not as hot anymore.
But biomedicine and development
of AIs for soil irrigation are super in.
What's biomedicine?
Biomedicine means biohacking.
The things
that help you live longer and enjoy
your health and life itself for longer.
Like erection at 80?
Exactly. This project will surely get
billions in investment money.
He has a great team. He has
the best team in the world.
And they're not Russian?
It's a mix. Some are Russian,
some aren't.
Why is he so reclusive?
- His wife gave an interview to the
Science and Life magazine.
- And Tatler.
I understand his wife is a big-time
local socialite.
They live an incredibly
complicated life.
They probably put together more parties
than anyone in the Valley.
His annual Gagarin Party, which just
happens to share its name with our fund,
gathers all the local big shots
in large quantities.
Every morning, somebody has breakfast at his place.
Every night, someone has dinner at his place.
Every week, a party
for around 30 people.
When he's in the Valley,
the house is never empty.
And it's complicated event management.
It's continuous event management.
- What for? For fun or for business?
- For business.
Milner says that venture capitalism lives
and dies by asymmetry of information.
One investor has a little information.
Another has a little more.
The investor with the most information
ultimately profits off of everyone else.
That's why, to possess more
information than anyone,
you need to maintain social
connections, the network,
with all the important people.
(title card music)
(Dud') Regarding the fact that everyone here
is either a startupper or an investor.
Dude in Moscow saves up
half a million dollars,
they're thinking of getting
a place in downtown.
He'd think differently here,
wouldn't he?
Down here, he'd think: "Why would
I buy something for half a mil?"
- "I'd rather found my own fund and start
giving out small..."
- Not even a fund!
Not even a fund.
They'd go to a meet-up
where startuppers present
their projects...
- A meet-up?
- Small gathering.
- There's several a day, right?
There's like 50.
If you open Events Near Me on Facebook,
it'll take ages to scroll through them all.
What is it like?
Guys just gather and..?
Yeah. Someone's found a place
where you can sit people down.
Someone has a friend
at Silicon Valley Bank,
they tell 'em, "We're doing a biotech
startup meet-up."
They go: "Hey, that's cool. We wanna
pitch in. We'll pay for the wine."
You have a little standing buffet,
a stage, a screen and projector setup.
They get guests from Google,
Facebook, engineers.
They're listening, going:
"I think this will take off."
"I wanna invest $10,000 in you."
That's how people raise their
first hundred thousand.
How does our fund work?
There's always a hierarchy, right? We know
that when we invest in 30 companies...
A little into each.
How much is "a little?"
- $200 to $400 thousand.
- Uh-huh.
This is after they've gotten
the initial, angel funding.
They have a product, some numbers.
Sometimes even revenue.
Out of those thirty,
ten will be doing very well.
Out of those ten, we'll pick five,
maybe seven, strongest ones,
and give them a million,
a million and a half more.
Out of them, one will be
doing super well,
and give a 3x return
on the fund's investment,
with another 3x return from the rest
of the companies combined.
I.e., to make a profit, you need to make at least
30 deals if you know what you're doing
or 100 deals if you don't know
what you're doing.
You said thirty. How many
of them will fail?
- Most of them.
- But others will make enough
to make up for it?
- Yes.
And make a profit.
Percentage of failures in
the Valley is very high.
A lot more startups fail
than take off.
Interestingly, the percentage of failed startups
today is likely much greater than 15 years ago.
When I travel...
My major is venture capital, the Valley,
innovative ecosystems, corporate innovations.
I travel a lot and I keep hearing:
"A lot more startups fail today in the Valley."
"Does that mean the Valley is losing
something, its secret sauce?"
Quite the opposite.
Because the business model
of startup financing
and the process of startup creation
have changed drastically.
If you have $50,000, 15 years ago,
you couldn't do anything with them.
Today, you can open a new startup
with this money.
All the startups that came
out of our studio
and all the new up-and-coming
startups making waves,
with rare exceptions, they don't need
to raise $5 million.
They can take off by raising $250 or $500
thousand, maybe a million.
Only when they're successful,
they'll then raise big money.
This means that if you had
a crazy idea 15 years ago,
but had no money,
you needed a crazy person sharing your
vision with $5 million in the bank.
Today, you need the same kind of crazy
person, only with $250,000 in the bank.
Those are much more common.
The most idiotic idea for an app
or startup in your memory?
(Doronichev laughs)
- Or the most weird and wacky?
- Hmm...
Like the app from the Silicon Valley
show that looked for...
Like the Bro app.
I believe you can't go wrong
with the Yo app here.
At some point... I feel this was
the quintessence of this rush
when people put money into
just about any mobile app.
Some guy made an app with only one function —
to send someone else a "Yo."
You type anything else.
And they had a whole...
People talked with straight faces that this
was the future of social communication,
that "Yo" could be used to express
many different feelings.
And... Yeah.
They successfully raised money.
They raised several million to develop Yo.
Didn't quite take off.
They teach the idea of investing
ever since you're a child here.
My kid's eight. I explained investing to him,
and now he invests money.
He has a portfolio that he funds
with the allowance money
that he's been saving up
for two years now.
He's investing this money in the four
companies he believes in.
He's investing in Google, Netflix,
Microsoft and Amazon.
Hold up! Virtually or for real?
No, I bought pieces of
those companies for him.
- Real Google shares?
- Yes.
He now follows his portfolio
and he understands
that money is not something
you hoard in a golden safe
and then spend on pretty things,
but rather that money is a tool.
It's a tool that has to work.
It's like your employee. You find them a job
and they do something useful.
Somewhere else, while you don't
actively use them.
All Americans understand this key idea
since they're little. It's very important.
When you understand this, you also
understand the idea of diversification,
i.e. that if you put all your "soldiers,"
your money in one place
without spreading them out
and lowering risks,
then you'll probably...
It's super risky.
You're likely to either make
very little or lose it all.
You don't get investment rounds
for sitting on your ass.
At some point, you have to
show a profit.
And this profit has to be
a multiple of...
Your profit combined with speed of your
growth determine your valuation.
You may bum your initial money
off people on the idea stage.
You can raise $500,000, a million, two million in
investment money with just your idea and your name.
"My name is Yuriy Dud'.
I'm super successful on YouTube."
"I have this idea for a platform to promote
up-and-coming YouTube faces."
"Here are some designs and ideas.
Please, give me funding to get started."
At that stage, yeah.
How much do you think
we could get?
I think you could raise two
million on the seed stage.
- Dollars?
- Yeah.
- What do I do with them?
Depends on your business idea,
but you'll probably hire engineers.
If you're smart about it, you'll hire engineers
in Russia or Belarus or something.
'Cause it's gonna be much cheaper
and you'll be able to hire some super talented
guys that you wouldn't be able to afford here.
With that money,
you'll build your MVP,
the initial version of your product.
My what?
MVP, minimum viable product.
In my world, that stands for
"most valuable player."
(Doronichev laughs)
- (Dud') That's why I got confused.
- Gotcha!
You'll build the initial version
of your product
that will prove to the investors and you that
you have a so-called product-market fit,
i.e. that your product does indeed
satisfy an existing demand.
Once you see that people are returning
and the product's growing,
you'll go and get the next round,
this time, for expansion.
You'll get your Round A,
[Round A is the second or third round of capital raising.]
[It starts when the firm enters the market, begins]
[serial production and hires a full team]
which you'll spend on growing your product as
quickly as possible without getting sidetracked
[Round A is the second or third round of capital raising.]
[It starts when the firm enters the market, begins]
[serial production and hires a full team]
to millions and billions
of users.
In Russia, where the entrepreneurship culture is
far less evolved than here, there's a stereotype:
young startuppers raise capital, then quickly
spend it on huge offices and expensive cars —
all the self-gratifying things that have
nothing to do with the business.
Does this ever happen here?
Well, anything's possible.
With tens of thousands of startups,
anything's possible.
I'd say that local investors are
much more professional.
Because funding startups, investors
are funding specific entrepreneurs.
They always keep their
finger on the pulse.
They also know what to expect.
Particularly, when startuppers
don't exactly act right,
smart investors immediately know what to look at,
how to assist and what to prevent.
That's why situations like what you
described are possible,
but they're extremely rare.
Because here...
If we look at the most
successful startups,
what they spend on private jets after they've
become multi-billion companies is irrelevant,
because starting out,
they normally rent the cheapest office
or even manage without one these days,
they save on everything,
and certainly don't buy
expensive cars.
- The idea can come from someone who's
not a programmer, right?
- Of course.
The idea comes from someone
with a vision for a product.
In your head, you're like: "I'm reaching
this audience and solving this problem."
That's what product managers do,
or in the case of a startup,
that's usually the founder.
Not all founders are programmers?
A lot of them aren't.
The most common setup for a typical
tech company is two founders,
this is very common,
one's with a product/business vision,
i.e. a people person and a problem
person who arranges things,
the other's a tech guy.
It's a common synergy that has
proven its effectiveness.
Like Richard and Erlich
from Silicon Valley?
Yeah, sort of.
At 23, you signed a deal that
made you a millionaire.
[YEVGENIY NEVGEN]
[28 years old]
[Co-founder of the selfie mask app MSQRD]
At 23, you signed a deal that
made you a millionaire.
[YEVGENIY NEVGEN]
[28 years old]
[Co-founder of the selfie mask app MSQRD]
Correct.
[YEVGENIY NEVGEN]
[28 years old]
[Co-founder of the selfie mask app MSQRD]
Can you briefly tell us about it?
About the deal itself?
About how you created
the app MSQRD,
which took off so well that it got
purchased by Facebook.
Well, I didn't create it myself.
We had a pretty big team.
In short, I started coding at 14.
I always dreamt of creating startups.
I read about it on the internet,
in magazines.
I founded several companies.
My childhood friend Sergey Gonchar
happened to move here.
Together, we founded several
companies.
Eventually, we designed
the mobile app MSQRD,
which quickly became
rather popular.
At some point, it appeared on the radar of
several major players, including Facebook.
We did a lot of thinking and decided this was
the right move at this stage in our careers
and agreed to sell
the company to Facebook.
This was December 25, 2015.
I was browsing App Store.
I regularly download App Store's top 200 or top 500,
whatever's new, always on the lookout for new stuff.
And I read in some local
Belarusian news
that they'd held a hackathon
with such and such new projects.
I read about it and was like:
"Cool idea!"
It said they'd promised to release
the app by Catholic Christmas.
I'm like: "Hey, it's the 25th. Let's see
if they kept their promise."
They had. It just released.
I clicked on it.
I open it and go: "This is nice.
This will take off."
"This will definitely take off. I even know
how I'm gonna promote it."
I check out the publisher.
It's an Indian name.
"Yauheni Neuhen."
When you transliterate Belarusian names
into English, they always look funny.
It actually was Yavgeniy Nevgen,
you know?
"Yauheni Neuhen."
I thought it was Indian, and was like:
"Wait, I read about Belarusians!"
I find him on Facebook and
start typing a message,
and it loads the history, showing that he's been
trying to reach me for 18 months,
but Facebook's been filtering it out,
so I never knew.
I got so embarrassed.
We agreed to meet. I talked
to him and Yura Gurskiy,
[Yuriy Gurskiy is a Belarusian IT entrepreneur.]
[Was a mentor and investor of projects]
[like Flo, Prisma, MSQRD,Maps.Me]
whom he already knew —
Gurskiy was the project's mentor.
[Yuriy Gurskiy is a Belarusian IT entrepreneur.]
[Was a mentor and investor of projects]
[like Flo, Prisma, MSQRD,Maps.Me]
They said: "We don't need money at the moment.
Nothing to spend on just yet."
[Yuriy Gurskiy is a Belarusian IT entrepreneur.]
[Was a mentor and investor of projects]
[like Flo, Prisma, MSQRD,Maps.Me]
"But we could use help in the States."
"You're in the States.
Help us get big in the States."
"We have 500 users.
We wanna get big."
- I started...
- 500?
- 500 users total.
I was user #515.
It was basically all friends of Zhenia,
Seriozha and another Zhenia.
[*Second most popular local social network in Russia.]
[Mostly used by the older generation.]
Can you explain what MSQRD is to people
who still use Odnoklassniki*?
They're masks that appeared on people's faces
when they made selfies or shot videos?
Instagram introduced these masks
after they bought you?
Yes, on Instagram and in other
Facebook products,
like Messenger and
the Facebook app itself,
it's our technology, our platform
and our masks.
So Facebook didn't just buy your app?
They bought your solution
and started integrating it
into their products?
Yeah, the idea was to buy
the team
that created the solution
and all the artwork
and the solution itself.
They didn't much care
about the app itself.
They wanted to introduce this feature
in other Facebook products.
Let me get this straight. When a company
like Facebook buys an app,
they're not buying an App Store icon —
they're buying the solution?
Of course. In most cases,
pretty much always,
Facebook has little interest
in the product's users,
because Facebook has...
- Enough of its own.
- ...several billion users. Billions!
Few can match that number.
That's why they buy solutions and
the people behind those solutions.
- This was in March of 2016?
- Yes.
Were Instagram stories
around at the time?
That's was Facebook's plan — to launch
stories with masks as a day one feature.
- So they launched after?
- Yes.
I understand that one of the reasons
stories took off so well
was the abundance of strapped on
extras, including masks?
...Of various artistic tools, yeah.
Draw something, put on a mask.
Now I understand the idea
behind the deal.
I get why they did it, 'cause when
you buy an app with —
how many users did you have,
ten million?
Thirty.
Thirty at the time.
Okay. Whatever.
...What do you do with them?
Why buy you?
Why not hire one of you and have
them explain how it works?
Well, for starters, the technology
itself wasn't unique.
There were even similar open-source
solutions available online.
The base technology
is called Face Tracking.
Those technologies were available — you could
download it from github or something.
Our technology, developed by
MSQRD's co-founder
Zhenia Zatepiakin,
he's the creator of this technology,
it was the fastest solution
for mobile phones.
As you know, mobile phones have certain
limitations in terms of performance.
Zhenia Zatepiakin's scientific
work aimed to develop
an algorithm that would be as precise and
as fast as possible on mobile phones.
We did a cool stunt with
Jimmy Kimmel.
- That was you?
- Yeah.
- He didn't notice you first?
His director followed Zhenia Zatepiakin,
one of the co-founders, on Twitter.
Zhenia told me.
I went and checked it out,
and sent him a direct message,
saying: "Hey! Heard you liked
MSQRD?"
He said: "Yeah,Jimmy's daughter
and I love it."
"Cool app. Guys did well."
I'm like: "Can I call you?"
We talked.
I did my homework —
I watched like 20 episodes of Kimmel Live,
found out he didn't like Matt Damon.
His girlfriend had left him
for Matt Damon.
And every episode, he says:
"We have..."
For those who don't know,
Kimmel Live is Evening Urgant.
- One of Evening Urgants.
- Yeah, there's lots of them here.
They're all alike.
And he's been making fun of
Matt Damon for years?
"We'll have Matt Damon on." Followed by:
"My apologies to Matt Damon. We ran out of time."
I went: "Jimmy, how about
we make a mask of you?"
He says: "Can you make one
of Guillermo?" He's like our...
- Hrustaliov?
- Hrustaliov. That's their Guillermo.
I went: "No problem. We'll throw in
a Matt Damon mask."
"For you to try on."
He laughed.
We couldn't make it in time
before he needed to go on air.
And he just said: "You know what? Screw it.
You have a great app. I'll show it off as is."
He showed us once. They fooled
around with it and laughed.
It aired. People noticed the app.
We later finished the mask,
sent it to him and said:
"Jimmy, here's your mask. Here's Guillermo's.
No Matt though — we ran out of time."
He laughed for five minutes
non-stop on the phone.
He said: "Well, now I just have to
feature you again."
And gave us like five minutes
of screen time.
Five days later, you closed
the Facebook deal?
Not closed yet.
It was in the process.
- The deal took four days to close?
- It was all done very fast.
It coincided with the weekend, and we
had to pay the lawyers double.
For some reason, Facebook wanted
to do it as quickly as possible.
Probably to avoid this information
from spreading to other corporations
who could contact us with
a better counter-offer.
They didn't want any
setbacks or leaks.
So they wanted to close the deal
as quickly as possible.
You mean you had to stay in the office
round the clock, at night too,
while the lawyers were handling
the paperwork?
Or you weren't there physically?
They didn't spend four days STRAIGHT
doing the paperwork.
We didn't spend four days
in the office with the lawyers.
It involved different people:
Belarusian lawyers, Facebook lawyers,
our American lawyers.
It was a lot of work, and it was
done in two shifts:
Belarusian office and American office.
How is your work evaluated
in these situations?
Through discussion.
Depends on your role.
If you're a strategic advisor that does
the M&A, then it's 4%, 5% or 6%.
[M&A stands for "mergers and acquisitions," i.e. a deal]
[that merges two or more companies into on.]
If you're a strategic advisor that does
M&A, then it's 4%, 5% or 6%.
[M&A stands for "mergers and acquisitions," i.e. a deal]
[that merges two or more companies into on.]
If you simply introduced them and they signed
the deal themselves, you get 1%.
Zhenia Nevgen became
a multimillionaire after this deal?
Zhenia Nevgen is a very talented
and successful young man.
Can't confirm any numbers.
Millions of bucks at 23.
Is that a burden?
They asked me about a month after
the deal at some conference in Minsk
what was different
in my new life.
I said, "Now, I take the taxi."
'Cause before that,
we used to ride the bus.
That's how the first
few years went.
The money we were getting...
Importantly, we didn't get the entire
sum all at once.
There wasn't a moment where all the money
for the deal instantly appeared in our account.
They paid gradually, and it
actually took a while.
Also, we tried to invest the money
as soon as we got it.
We didn't start spending on
expensive things or something.
We only got the things we desperately
needed as soon as we got the money,
but there was never a moment where
our world view suddenly changed.
(title card music)
What is that?
That's our new app, currently being developed
by the ex-MSQRD team. It's called Loóna.
Like the Russian rock band.
It helps people fall asleep...
or get in the mood to sleep —
relax after work,
forget about the...
A lot of people flick through
Instagram and watch YouTube
because they can't just get into their
bed and fall asleep after work.
I know that a lot... I can tell you're one
of those people who instantly crash out.
Yeah, totally.
- But...
- You don't idle on Instagram before falling asleep?
- No.
Well, in reality, a large number
of people can't fall asleep quickly.
They keep thinking about
the events of the day,
their issues and worries, their plans for
tomorrow, and they need a distraction.
What do you do here?
You color?
We have a number of scenes.
They're all particular places.
- So it's mechanical in...
- What happens if you swipe?
When you're done coloring the scene,
it puts on a sleep story.
It's a story about the place
from the scene.
The user shuts off the screen, puts the device
down on their night stand
and listens to this story that
helps them doze off.
- The story's in English?
- Yes, in English.
So the Belarusians immediately
went global again.
We'll probably add Russian
language too.
What do you think about MSQRD?
I'm astounded by how this project was
starting out and what it's become,
and how this in a way led to the explosion
of the Belarusian wing of the industry.
There's a ton of projects right now created by
MSQRD's co-founders or former employees.
This is a success for the CIS
as a whole.
'Cause now, when we
present ourselves,
many know about the successes of
MSQRD, Prisma, Wargaming.
This makes it much easier
to get funding.
Reliable gang?
Yeah! If those guy made it,
why can't these?
Because there hadn't been too many cases
of successful company sales in the Valley.
- (Dud') Your dog is from Belarus?
- Yes! From Minsk.
It's a Swiss mountain dog,
but it hails from Belarus.
- Was she a gift from your partners?
- No, I bought her myself.
We wanted to get this
breed specifically,
There were lines for them in Moscow.
The puppies are sold before they're conceived.
It's crazy.
"We're mating the dog and
the bitch in three months."
"We'll probably have 4 or 5 puppies."
"But we're selling them now."
(Davidov laughs)
(Dud') Damn! Sounds like a startup!
It's crazy. My aunt said: "I know a breeder, but she's
in Minsk. You'll have to drive for the doggie."
We did. Went and got the dog
and came back.
You're obsessed with Belarus,
aren't you?
No! The dog was my first and least successful
Belarusian investment. All others were great.
Legend, or maybe truth, has it
that Masquerade Technologies was born
as a result a 48-hour hackathon.
There's some truth to it, yeah.
You came together... A hackathon is an event
where programmers develop all sorts of things.
The reason I know this isn't because I'm smart.
Sports.ru just hosted a bunch of them.
So I got to see it.
That's where you first showed
your whole thing with masks.
I read that one of the masks you showed
off was a mask with mustache.
(Nevgen laughs)
It belonged to Aleksandr Lukashenko.
Is that true?
It's true. But this mask was never
available to the public.
Funny story, actually.
When we came to the hackathon,
we had some things prepped.
Most importantly, we had
the face tracking technology,
but we didn't have everything
ready for the app.
Well, hackathon rules state you
shouldn't have ANYTHING ready.
Yeah.
Of course, we did the majority of
development at the hackathon.
We realized we couldn't put in all
the masks that we wanted in time.
We decided to use some of the
most recognizable faces.
Well, who's the most famous,
most recognizable Belarusian?
So yeah, at the hackathon,
we had this mask.
But we knew that...
...we couldn't go general public with it, so we got
rid of this mask after the hackathon.
Why not?
For starters, our criminal code prohibits
offending the president.
That was a sufficient reason.
Fellow countries.
Nevgen's currently involved
with the startup Flo.
Yeah. He's an investor.
- It's a menstrual cycle app?
- Yeah. It's great!
There's a huge number, like 80 million women
around the world use it to track their cycle.
And it brings money?
It does. There's a subscription fee.
The cycle can slip. It's not synced
with the calendar.
It depends on a bunch of factors.
Knowing when your cycle's
coming up is very handy.
With Flo, several hundred thousand women every
month plan to get pregnant and get pregnant.
The fact itself that people now know what's going
on with them, their body and their health,
that makes us happy.
This is a calling for us.
It's a dream.
Our bedtime app Loóna.
Again, it helps people become more productive,
because they get a good night's sleep.
We know we're having an impact.
We're doing something
meaningful and valuable.
That's very important to us.
Who's developing it?
Other Belarusians? Belarusians
in Gomel, in Grodno, in Vitebsk?
Yes, it's made by Belarusian guys, but...
It's getting harder and harder
to hire in Belarus.
There's a lot of IT companies
in Belarus today.
There's series competition
for quality staff.
We hire people from
all over the world.
We bring in people from
Ukraine and Russia.
We meet them at the airport,
help them situate, sit them down.
For this particular product, we're currently
running a pretty large HR campaign.
Hiring...
You're looking for... Hold on. You're telling me
that Belarusian engineers are so loaded
that you have to hire
in Russia and Ukraine?
- They're in such high demand that you have to
bring in people from other countries?
- It would appear so.
(Nevgen laughs)
You can certainly say that software
engineer is a very popular job in Belarus.
Why are there so many of you?
- Software engineers?
- Yeah! Belarus is like a motherlode.
These guys created Wargaming.
These ones made Masquerade.
And you just keep going.
Why?
Lots of smart people.
No oil. Maybe that's why.
No oil?
Well, there's a little.
But barely.
What a reason!
- I think there's a link.
- Why?
The link is that when you have a small
country with a small domestic market,
you have to produce things
for the entire planet Earth.
Maybe that's also the reason why Israel
is such a big IT country. Estonia too.
Small country. No domestic demand.
You have no choice but to come up
with something to make money.
They don't have domestic demand.
Meaning, they can't sell
anything back in Belarus.
They don't have the money
in Belarus to buy it.
Say, a Russian entrepreneur starts
developing an innovative product.
Who are they creating it for? For Gazprom,
or MTS, or Sberbank, or any other local...
- Or the Russian market in general.
- Exactly.
They start making money off of it,
and they can no longer go foreign.
- Why?
- Because business is different
everywhere.
All companies have their own mentalities.
You need different products...
- And Belarusians?
- Belarusians don't have any local buyers!
They aim for the American or the global
market from the start.
Two countries are like that:
Belarus and Israel.
Also, their government
is pretty chill about it.
Funny, isn't it? The head of
the Technopark came here.
[In December of 2017, Belarus passed a law concerning IT.]
[It made cryptocurrencies and the blockchain legal,]
[established English law institutes and visa-free entry]
[for international employees of the local IT cluster]
Funny, isn't it? The head of
the Technopark came here.
[In December of 2017, Belarus passed a law concerning IT.]
[It made cryptocurrencies and the blockchain legal,]
[established English law institutes and visa-free entry]
[for international employees of the local IT cluster]
- Right?
- He's a state official back in Belarus.
[In December of 2017, Belarus passed a law concerning IT.]
[It made cryptocurrencies and the blockchain legal,]
[established English law institutes and visa-free entry]
[for international employees of the local IT cluster]
They told me: "Kolia, meet with him.
He's a cool dude."
[In December of 2017, Belarus passed a law concerning IT.]
[It made cryptocurrencies and the blockchain legal,]
[established English law institutes and visa-free entry]
[for international employees of the local IT cluster]
Wait, what's a technopark?
[*High-tech business area in Moscow.]
- They have this place in Minsk...
- It's like a Minsk Skolkovo*?
- It's a Skolkovo made right.
Right?
As I talk to him, I realize that
they have the right idea.
For example, he said: "If a Belarusian is moving
to the Silicon Valley to found a startup
"or to work at Google,
"I'll help them every way I can."
"I'll go to their place and
pack their things."
"Because I know that they'll
either come back
"with knowledge and money,
"but most importantly knowledge
of how you do it right,
"or they'll hire Belarusians
from over there,
"because they know them
and how to work with them,
"thus we'll have money and
expertise flow our way."
Okay, you get an A in GR for massaging
the Belarusians as an investor.
Hold on, I was being honest!
Sure, but then how come the CEO of Wargaming
has been living on Cyprus for so many years?
[Viktor Kisliy, the owner and CEO of Wargaming.net,]
[moved to Cyprus in 2011. The company also moved its]
[headquarters to the island — to efficiently control its]
[international operations. The company's biggest office]
[is still in Minsk, the workplace of game developers and]
[coordinators of the other 15 offices. In 2016, Bloomberg]
[estimated that Kisliy's net worth had surpassed $1 billion]
It's not easy to run a big business
in Belarus. If you look at...
[Viktor Kisliy, the owner and CEO of Wargaming.net,]
[moved to Cyprus in 2011. The company also moved its]
[headquarters to the island — to efficiently control its]
[international operations. The company's biggest office]
[is still in Minsk, the workplace of game developers and]
[coordinators of the other 15 offices. In 2016, Bloomberg]
[estimated that Kisliy's net worth had surpassed $1 billion]
Again, if the Belarusian government
supports all startuppers,
[Viktor Kisliy, the owner and CEO of Wargaming.net,]
[moved to Cyprus in 2011. The company also moved its]
[headquarters to the island — to efficiently control its]
[international operations. The company's biggest office]
[is still in Minsk, the workplace of game developers and]
[coordinators of the other 15 offices. In 2016, Bloomberg]
[estimated that Kisliy's net worth had surpassed $1 billion]
(interrupts Davidov) how come the head
of the BIGGEST Belarusian corporation...
[Viktor Kisliy, the owner and CEO of Wargaming.net,]
[moved to Cyprus in 2011. The company also moved its]
[headquarters to the island — to efficiently control its]
[international operations. The company's biggest office]
[is still in Minsk, the workplace of game developers and]
[coordinators of the other 15 offices. In 2016, Bloomberg]
[estimated that Kisliy's net worth had surpassed $1 billion]
And Prokopenia served prison time.
[Venture investor Viktor Prokopenia was detained]
[in spring of 2015 for unregistered business activity.]
[Prokopenia was released in late 2015.]
[In February of 2016, the case was dropped]
- Yeah. How come?
- I mean, that's insane!
[Venture investor Viktor Prokopenia was detained]
[in spring of 2015 for unregistered business activity.]
[Prokopenia was released in late 2015.]
[In February of 2016, the case was dropped]
I'm not saying they're
great and perfect.
[Venture investor Viktor Prokopenia was detained]
[in spring of 2015 for unregistered business activity.]
[Prokopenia was released in late 2015.]
[In February of 2016, the case was dropped]
They're moving
in the right direction.
[Venture investor Viktor Prokopenia was detained]
[in spring of 2015 for unregistered business activity.]
[Prokopenia was released in late 2015.]
[In February of 2016, the case was dropped]
We don't even have
THAT in Russia!
You know this joke about
Belarusian business?
Belarusian businessmen are like
passengers on a public bus:
one half is sitting,
the other's shaking.
(Davidov) Yeah...
Then how can you say that..?
If Elon Musk was Belarusian,
he'd still be sitting for PayPal.
Popular joke. Also works for Russia.
I'm not saying you should do
business in Belarus.
That's just my answer to why
Belarusian IT is on the rise.
It's a combination of
a non-existing market,
lack of state meddling
in the early stages...
If a Belarusian... Why do startuppers
do so well in Belarus?
You can't rob them.
They have jack shit.
And so they support them.
If they build a big company over there,
then sure, trouble will ensue.
A ton of people will suddenly go:
"Hey, they've got money!"
That makes sense.
But startuppers have nothing.
And there's no market.
And the country's dirt-poor.
That's why the first thing you make
competes with Google.
You have your own Skolkovo,
don't you?
Hi-Tech Park.
- And unlike Skolkovo, it works?
- Yeah.
HTP is a state organization that
surrounds itself with tech companies.
The biggest benefit for these
companies is tax reduction.
You have to meet certain criteria.
You have to have a business plan.
You have to adhere to this plan.
Then they accept your company
as a resident of the HTP,
and you pay reduced taxes.
- Go create and develop?
- Yeah. But follow regulations.
Regulations, sure.
It's in Minsk, right?
The company doesn't necessarily
have to be somewhere physically.
It could be located anywhere.
So the Park doesn't exist?
- It exists.
- Yeah?
They have learning facilities,
they have a coworking,
they have offices for lease
for IT companies,
but it's mostly spread around.
(title card music)
(muffled street sounds)
[In 2020, the world faced the coronavirus pandemic.]
[In early March, the Silicon Valley instituted]
[a strict isolation policy]
(Dud') How's your dog doing?
[In 2020, the world faced the coronavirus pandemic.]
[In early March, the Silicon Valley instituted]
[a strict isolation policy]
The dog's doing wonderful.
It's super happy.
Some friends told me their dog had had
a rare injury — a dislocated tail.
'Cause everyone's always at home,
and it kept wagging its tail 24/7.
Mine's holding in there.
She has a strong tail.
(Dud') We showed off the Good House.
[The Good House is the name of Doronichev's co-housing]
[project in San Francisco, where he shares his house]
[with Dumik and other startuppers]
This was all very sweet,
when people could come out.
[The Good House is the name of Doronichev's co-housing]
[project in San Francisco, where he shares his house]
[with Dumik and other startuppers]
But without the freedom
to leave the house,
[The Good House is the name of Doronichev's co-housing]
[project in San Francisco, where he shares his house]
[with Dumik and other startuppers]
is it still sunshine and rainbows?
I'm grateful that I'm facing
this situations in this house
and in these circumstances,
because... Here's why.
A friend called me the other day
and said: "Our house has a pool."
"We're chilling in the pool."
I went:
"Well, my house... has people."
"...Other people that you can
talk to from six feet away."
He was like, "Daaamn!"
You know?
- In these circumstances, your friends, family
and neighbors are priceless.
- He envies you?
- Of course!
People to spend time in your
backyard with.
We comply with the rules of isolation, of course.
We occupy different floors in the house,
but it's a shared yard.
We comply with the rules of isolation,
but we might go to the yard,
sit down at a safe distance and talk,
drink tea or sing songs with a guitar.
We do various events in Zoom.
For example, my housemates...
Dima Dumik started this cool
dance in Zoom
that brings together hundreds of
people from all over the world.
Everyone's dancing at home,
but it's like they're dancing together.
It proved to be a great workout,
both physically and mentally.
Everyone in the Valley either worked
remotely or was prepared to.
I.e., everyone had the infrastructure.
So once the initial news from
China started coming in,
people took their kids out of schools
and went into self-isolation.
That view behind your back
is called self-isolation, right?
I'm super lucky. I know that it's as if
I was preparing for this,
for what's going on right now.
I'm even luckier than it looks!
My in-laws are stuck here with us.
Is it lucky though?
Of course it is! They're saints!
They tolerate my kids.
When we started to go crazy
in the first two weeks,
when you realize your bed's also
become your workplace
where you can sometimes find chicken
bones from last night's dinner
and where your cat naps,
all that stuff,
we wanted to do something
about it.
So my wife Tania put
a schedule on the wall
and we started sort of
imitating a normalcy.
We started to wake up on time,
put on our work clothes,
go outside and walk in circles
around the house for half an hour
to imitate the feeling of having
walked to school,
come back inside and only then get
on our laptops and start working.
That way, things started to resemble
our normal lives.
We shot several hours of footage
exploring how the Valley worked,
how startups were created,
all those connections
and inspiring stories
and all the other
interaction networks.
Is it all now obsolete?
No, it'll be that way forever.
Some things will stay,
others will change.
Some things will become much stronger,
others will probably go away forever.
What do you think will
go away forever?
I'd say, the excessive
prioritization of location will.
It's one of the changes the Valley
was already moving towards.
This microlocation: working specifically in
Mountain View or specifically in Palo Alto,
or specifically in San Francisco.
This was already slowly changing.
Some had moved across
the Bay to Oakland
simply because it was cheaper and
had more to offer to a family.
Some had moved to
the surrounding suburbs.
Some Valley companies would go:
"We'll have hubs over here, here and here."
For example, Square said:
"Our new hub is work from home."
[Square is an American tech company that develops]
[solutions for receiving and processing online payments]
For example, Square said:
"Our new hub is work from home."
[Square is an American tech company that develops]
[solutions for receiving and processing online payments]
Why was this localized
hyperconcentration so important?
Because you could meet up with anyone in the
industry in like 10 minutes, or just bump into them.
It's like this magic soup.
Now that this magic soup
has moved to Zoom,
turns out, it's doesn't really matter
where you are physically.
The spirit and the culture matter.
Well, the spirit and the culture
will definitely persist.
It's gonna be one big village,
only spread out geographically.
What about all the unique features
like competitiveness,
the endless influx of fresh blood,
the tolerance towards the crazy
and the unconventional,
the tolerance to failure,
Stanford as this citadel
of enlightenment
that attracts fresh blood,
fresh minds and all that stuff?
Will they all persist despite
the coronavirus
and the fact that you don't have to
be next to others physically?
Well done on the key feature
checklist, actually.
Yeah, it'll all persist, of course.
Social connections change too.
It's not just harder to work —
managers have a harder time
supervising their subordinates.
Many managers switch to the so-called
"seagull management,"
where you fly in, yell at and poop
on everyone and fly away agay.
You don't actually know what
your people are doing,
'cause you can't see them,
and it's all very unusual.
When your toolset is lacking,
you turn into a seagull.
(after laughing silently for 10 seconds straight)
"Seagull management!"
Damn! So accurate!
I recently read about some
guys from Ukraine
that had founded a startup
for restaurants.
Their app lets you order food before
you arrive at the restaurant.
They were in the middle of raising
money, and you'd think
that their startup would've
keeled over.
But that's the thing about Valley mentality —
quick adaptability.
They instantly repurposed their startup
to help restaurants that never
offered takeout before
quickly learn to process orders
and offer takeout.
This adaptability to changing environment
is the very DNA of the Valley.
We're witnessing it right now.
Is Zoom the biggest company
of the coronavirus era?
I believe so.
Zoom and all the remote medicine
and remote education services.
[Internet security experts call Zoom a fairly vulnerable app.]
[Hackers are abusing this. In early April 2020, thousands]
[of private video calls were uploaded to the internet]
Zoom and all the remote medicine
and remote education services.
[Internet security experts call Zoom a fairly vulnerable app.]
[Hackers are abusing this. In early April 2020, thousands]
[of private video calls were uploaded to the internet]
There's a ton of non-consumer
companies that work with businesses
[Internet security experts call Zoom a fairly vulnerable app.]
[Hackers are abusing this. In early April 2020, thousands]
[of private video calls were uploaded to the internet]
that also benefited
from the situation.
But Zoom's up there of course.
Zoom's user base increased twentyfold.
- Twenty?
- From ten million to two hundred million.
What is that if you convert it
into money?
It's like a spike, but most people won't
actually renew their paid subscriptions.
The important part is that user
habits are being changed.
User habit has unbelievable momentum.
When a company manages to turn its product
into a user habit for a large swath of people,
that's guaranteed success.
Zoom is currently becoming a user
habit for 200 million people.
As a result, they'll multiply their money,
maybe not 20 times, but 10 times for sure.
How much were they worth
before the corona?
Their stock didn't go up by that much.
Maybe about 30%.
Currently, Zoom's worth is like
Uber and Lyft combined.
[Lyft is an American taxi service]
[and Uber's biggest competitor]
But that's not much more
than what it used to be.
[Lyft is an American taxi service]
[and Uber's biggest competitor]
Because investors already had
high expectations for them.
One, two or three companies that
thrived the most with corona?
Mine did.
Very humble!
I'm not being coy. It's just easier
to talk about things that I know.
We at Ecwid are super happy
that it didn't affect us much.
In fact, we're having an easier
time now in some respects.
The reason is, what we do is help businesses
go online, we've always been doing this.
The demand for it
is now enormous.
We've always been a work-from-
home-friendly business.
We never had set work hours.
No one's supervised your presence.
You could not show up at all.
Previously, we used to be
work from home-friendly.
Now, we're work from office-unfriendly.
You used to choose between home and office.
Office is no longer an option, is all.
That's why the transition
was so easy.
We closed our offices much earlier than
you had to in California or in Russia.
That part of organizing
work got easier.
At the same time,
the demand tripled.
In this context, we really
wanna act responsibly.
The reason is because this is where
the Valley mentality comes into play.
Which part of it?
The part where you always shoot
to win big in the future
rather than cash out today.
We know we're good on money.
When small businesses
face this kind of shit,
our purpose is to help them.
That's why we... We had free
programs to begin with.
We considerably expanded
our free programs.
Made some previously paid
programs free.
Stuff like gift certificate support.
Businesses that had to
close down...
There's a local trend over here:
support your local food place.
(Dud') It's basically like futures
or donations, right?
Yeah, yeah. It's exactly that.
We moved those things to our free
programs to help those guys out.
We offer free... On a number of programs,
we just said: "We're charging you nothing in 2020."
"It's a bad year."
"Leap year."
"Let's not bring up money this year.
Just use our services."
It's super important, because there's
a concept in the Valley
called "long-term customer value,"
or LTV.
Your current profit is not as important
as this LTV statistic.
Are there any companies that
the corona straight up killed off?
Of course there are.
It killed off travel firms.
What about the big players?
The brands that we're used to.
Most of those brands
will get bailed out.
If it's an American brand,
Expedia, Booking.com,
all the airlines —
they'll bail 'em out.
They just print money for them,
essentially distributing their
losses across the nation.
In case of America, across the world, because
everyone depends on the dollar more or less.
Is it the government
that does this?
Yes, it's the government.
The government understands that a controlled
economic loss is a lesser evil
than 100,000 unemployed
in a certain business sector.
That's for a small sector.
For a large sector like air travel,
it could turn way uglier.
What do you think is gonna
happen to Tesla?
On our way to the Valley, we wanted
to test the Russian stereotypes like
"Musk is clueless!"
"Tesla is a bubble!"
Everyone we met told us
that it wasn't a bubble,
that they had infrastructure,
a product, yadda yadda.
What about now?
Tesla is a great company.
I have...
I dunno. Don't wanna stumble
around with the camera.
But I have a disassembled
bike outside.
I removed its battery,
'cause it's outta juice,
and I don't wanna go to the station
to touch any hoses. It can wait.
Car's empty too.
But Tesla is the only vehicle
I drive these days.
Because it's always charged.
Solar batteries on the roof.
It's complete autonomy.
I don't need anyone.
I love driving it. Moreover...
Is it a perfect company from
customer's point of view? No.
For example, I have to repair their
fancy extending handles all the time.
I recently called in Tesla service.
Again, they're perfectly
adapted to this world.
- Because I scheduled the visit
through their app.
- Ohh!
The guy came over. It's mobile service!
You don't have to go anywhere.
They come to you.
They fixed the handle and left.
I got a notification from the app
to pay for the service and I did.
That was it. They're perfectly
adapted to the corona world.
The corona world will obviously
come to an end. Tesla will stay.
It's a great company.
It's a great idea.
I'm sure Musk will figure it out.
I went to the vet to get my dog's
teeth checked up.
I made an appointment.
They said: "When you arrive,
don't leave your car. Just call us."
I go there. It's all covered in signs saying
"Don't leave car," "Don't go inside."
I called them, said I was there.
A nurse came out,
took the dog without
touching me or the car
and from a considerable
distance.
She went inside, and the doc
called me on the phone.
The doc and I talked on the phone the whole
way through. I explained everything.
Of course I'd filled out
all the forms online prior.
Afterward, they gave the dog back
to me, again no contact,
and called and said: "Please, give us your bank
card and insurance details so we could bill you."
Some tiny four-doctor vet
clinic in this village
turned into an online
operation in just one week,
digitized in every way: online payments,
online desk, online forms, e-signatures.
That's cool!
I hope all business will do this.
'Cause I always hated waiting
in line at the vet clinic.
Must say, I was never a follower of this
idea that the Valley was our savior,
that technology was everything.
I've always been skeptical
about these things:
"Are we sure we're doing a good thing,
or have we gone too far?"
But in this particular situation,
thanks to the Valley,
half of the world kept
going in some capacity.
We continue shopping,
ordering food,
going to school via Zoom,
working, et cetera.
Maybe this is wishful thinking,
but we figured that the place world
repair solutions would come from,
'cause the world will obviously require
repairs on a ton of its systems,
will be the Valley,
and places like it,
where you've got brains, money and
an established and sustainable setup
for said brains and money to work in tandem
for the betterment of the world.
Am I comforting myself here,
praying I don't end up jobless,
or does this ring true?
It does ring true. 'Cause even though
new connections aren't being made,
the brains and the money
haven't gone anywhere.
Neither has this place's
unique culture,
the culture of people who want to change
the world, improve it, help others —
all those local themes.
Each place has its own theme.
In Moscow, people want
to make money.
In New York, people want influence.
In the Valley, people want
to change the world.
Money is a means
and influence is a means to change
the world and leave your mark.
Whom do people envy here?
Those who left a mark.
Those who created something which
changed people's user habits.
Certainly, being with a group of people,
sharing the same physical space,
when it comes to creative
and artistic jobs,
you usually perform better
and more efficiently.
There is a sort of magic
of presence.
We do sorely miss it.
My productivity has dropped
dramatically.
Probably, by 50%.
I keep hearing it from
others too.
Meanwhile, all my colleagues
and I work more hours.
We spend more time
in video conferences.
But we get less work done.
So this sort of magic of human
communication
that you create with campuses, offices
and all kinds of artistic spaces,
it's missing right now.
But again, I think we'll adapt and might
even say we don't need any campuses.
Though we'll probably revert after realizing that we do
need physical communication and interaction.
Free food isn't going
away though, is it?
(laughs) I believe they'll keep
the free food.
Yeah, I think the free food
will stay.
Serioga sighed in relief!
(laughs) Serioga, come over!
We'll get you fed! (laughs)
As soon as they lift the ban,
come over, dude!
(title card music)
I understand that lately, more people
are coming specifically from Russia?
- You mean compared to Russia
previously?
- Yeah.
There was a spike, a couple of spikes, when
a lot of great NEW people came here.
I found myself surrounded
by people
whom I doubt I would've been able
to even meet in Moscow.
Given how great they are.
- Super talented guys.
- When was the spike?
After the launch of the Crimean campaign,
a lot of people moved here.
Did people start to flock here
after 2014?
In droves.
I was coming here knowing that two or three
people I knew had moved here before me.
I thought, "Okay,
I'll find people to talk to."
I moved and I started getting
messaged every day:
"Hey, Kolian! I moved too. Can you
clue me in on what's where?"
"What's up with local schools?
Where do I drop off my kids?"
Half of my course mates
had moved.
- What course?
- Like 15 people I went to college with.
- What course though?
- This was... Management Faculty.
Like 15 people from one course.
Out of, what, 200 people?
They were probably
the bottom, right?
That's the thing: people that moved
were the best of the best.
When programmers approach you these days,
in whatever way, and ask for advice:
"Should I move there?
Over there?"
What do you tell them?
- It's a sore subject for me.
- Pray tell?
I'm a serial migrant. I jumped
countries several times.
My base motive was...
There were a bunch. I'd come up
with business-related reasons too.
[*Derogatory name for Russia, made using its]
[English name and the diminutive suffix K.]
But I think the reality is very simple.
I was one of many who went:
"Gotta skip Rushka*!"
This sort of popular sentiment.
- Awful.
- It is awful! It's so dumb.
People don't understand that leaving your
country, usually, you're not the bottom.
They lament their living, but they're usually not
doing the worst in their country at the time.
When you move to another country,
you're resetting your social status.
As a migrant, you have to
develop new skills.
Most of the time, it's a net loss.
It differs from case to case, but usually,
emigration is a big mistake.
People don't get this for
one simple reason.
Their peers that left earlier
are a bad influence.
Here's how it works.
Their what?
People among their social
connections who'd left.
In reality, you'll feel awful
after migrating. Honestly.
It's not just me.
I watch other people.
There are a ton of downsides
to migrating.
No migrant will ever admit
that they're unhappy.
I have a pretty bloated ego,
so I can easily admit these
things without hurting it.
I can admit certain soar spots.
But most people can't. Admitting they'd made
a big mistake would hurt too much.
They can't come back.
Why? 'Cause they're weak?
Well, because you...
Most people will...
I have enough money.
I can move at any time. It'll cost me
a ton of money, but I don't mind.
Someone else will have committed. They'll have
gotten a new place, sold their old one.
This moving transaction is pretty expensive.
And you usually can't go back anymore.
It's also a very tough decision.
I remember how tough
it was to go back. Twice.
I made this decision twice. And both
times, I had to force myself.
"You giving up?"
And so on.
But I made it.
A typical person can't admit
this was a bad decision.
What they can do is project
happiness towards home,
because they can't project
happiness to the locals.
Locals probably get paid more
for the same work.
Locals live in a better
neighborhood.
They'll be doing so-so
compared to the locals.
But because there are others back
in Russia with a dream to LEAVE,
and since they'd made it,
they get this affirmation that they
did the right thing through others.
They project "I did good" on their
former countrymen.
Everybody dreams of the Valley,
don't they?
Not everybody.
A lot of people are like,
I don't wanna go anywhere.
Many say: "Screw your Valley.
It sucks. I wanna live in Europe."
- Do they tether themselves to Russia?
- Many do, yeah.
What do they do?
Work for people who moved West
or for Western companies,
or Chinese companies.
- What about our companies?
- Or for the state.
Or for the state?
You consider Yandex
state-owned too now?
No, it isn't yet. They soon will be.
But they're holding in there.
- They're like an islet of freedom.
- Does watching things unravel around
Yandex make you upset?
- It makes me very upset.
- What particularly upsets you?
You know, from the beginning, Yandex
was probably the most independent
island in the independent
sea of internet.
The culture of this company was mostly
built by Ilya Segalovich.
[Ilya Segalovich co-founded Yandex.]
[He died in 2013]
The culture of this company was mostly
built by Ilya Segalovich.
[Ilya Segalovich co-founded Yandex.]
[He died in 2013]
After he died, Yandex started
changing from the inside.
With constant external pressure,
it started to bend.
I don't it would have
if Ilya was around.
Simple, obvious question.
Why was your goal
to teach here,
rather than in MSU or NES
or any other place?
[NES, New Economic School,]
[private economic school in Moscow]
Why outside of Russia?
The most important thing for
a scientist is the community.
Second most important
are the students.
By "community" I mean
the research community.
You wanna work with accomplished people
who are smart and interesting to talk to.
Top universities usually have
very interesting research staffs.
In Stanford, each professor is not only
a leader in their area of expertise,
but also an incredibly
interesting person to talk to
about science... and not just science.
That's one.
Two, the students.
Quality of students here
is absolutely superb.
Third, surprisingly important
and something I didn't
fully appreciate at first
was that Stanford University is very
tolerant towards what you do.
On the one hand, you have to
achieve incredible success,
because sooner or later, they have to
give or deny you tenure.
[Tenure is an indefinite contract with a professor]
At some point, they'll make a judgment on whether
you'd become an apex scientist in your field.
But they're very calm about:
what research papers you write,
whom you do research with,
what specific subject
you're studying.
This freedom of research...
You know? You want
room to breathe!
Freedom of research is
unbelievably advanced here.
It's one of the things for which
I'm so grateful to this university.
Because when I first came here,
I was researching one thing,
and achieved success there.
But afterward, since I'd moved to work at
a university in the middle of Silicon Valley,
over the course of several years,
I got interested in a different subject.
I became interested in venture capital,
corporate innovation, et cetera.
And I believe I would've had a harder time
switching gears at a lot of other research centers.
Down here, it was very simple.
All the young boys and girls
watching now, thinking:
"That's it! I'm applying
to a tech faculty!"
"I wanna work at Google, or Facebook,
or something like that!"
Is there potential for
disappointment?
Of course. They WILL be
disappointed!
Could they run into a global,
strategic blunder
of the fact that in ten years, the world won't
need this many software engineers?
If they chase a made-up
goal like this,
they WILL end up disappointed.
I think if you pursue a particular area
only because someone told you
there's money in it, you might
be disappointed.
If you pursue your passion,
which will itself reinforce ambition for
perfection and perpetual curiosity,
you'll do great.
You said a lot of things in Russia
distracted from doing business.
- Yeah.
- What exactly?
There's always a sort of
uncertainty.
Stuff like: will I get a surprise
inspection today?
As soon as you reach a certain level,
they might become interested in you.
I mean...
Also, the legal side of doing
business is rather...
It takes a lot more resources
than some place like America.
There are cases where...
For example, Fiodor Ovchinnikov,
the founder of Dodo Pizza...
Cops found drugs in the bathroom
of one of the restaurants
[In February and May of 2018, Ovchinnikov was questioned]
[as a witness after an anonymous tip that his pizzeria]
[chain was a foil for a distribution network of Latin American]
[drugs. According to the detective, drug stashes]
[were found in several restaurants of the chain.]
[Ovchinnikov said that this was an attempt to frame him]
and started dragging him from one
legal agency to another.
[In February and May of 2018, Ovchinnikov was questioned]
[as a witness after an anonymous tip that his pizzeria]
[chain was a foil for a distribution network of Latin American]
[drugs. According to the detective, drug stashes]
[were found in several restaurants of the chain.]
[Ovchinnikov said that this was an attempt to frame him]
[In February and May of 2018, Ovchinnikov was questioned]
[as a witness after an anonymous tip that his pizzeria]
[chain was a foil for a distribution network of Latin American]
[drugs. According to the detective, drug stashes]
[were found in several restaurants of the chain.]
[Ovchinnikov said that this was an attempt to frame him]
- He created a... He's from Siktivkar, isn't he?
- Yeah.
[In February and May of 2018, Ovchinnikov was questioned]
[as a witness after an anonymous tip that his pizzeria]
[chain was a foil for a distribution network of Latin American]
[drugs. According to the detective, drug stashes]
[were found in several restaurants of the chain.]
[Ovchinnikov said that this was an attempt to frame him]
He created an amazing company
with lots of positive energy.
It's a global pizza chain, right?
[Dodo Pizza has over 600 restaurants in 13 countries]
But they search him in Russia and start
this whole drug affair. It's absurd.
As soon as you become someone,
they'll come to collect.
Or this business where they
clamp down on the freedom
of speech.
Say, you've created VK.
You have this new media with
communities for oppositionists.
They start clipping your wings.
Those are the differences and
limitations that I don't much care for,
because they're in the way
of my goals.
It's not a bad thing, is it?
The Belarusians said it best:
the fact that we left was
great for the country.
Because... Think about it. I invest
a ton of money in Russia myself.
I pay a shit ton of taxes
in Russia.
A lot more than what I was
paying when I lived there.
I've created a couple
hundred jobs in Russia.
What do you do there?
Development of a bunch of
companies from our portfolio.
Wait, but I thought it was better if people like that lived in their home country?
They're open to the world
and stuff.
I mean, they leave and don't plan
to come back, do they?
- I mean those 15 from your course?
- Quite the opposite.
We're all very different in that...
People from the sausage migration
wave were leaving to leave.
["Sausage migration" denotes people who left late]
[USSR and early Russia in late '80s and early '90s]
People from the sausage migration
wave were leaving to leave.
["Sausage migration" denotes people who left late]
[USSR and early Russia in late '80s and early '90s]
They were going AWAY,
not TO.
We left TO and IN ORDER TO.
We left to learn.
We left to achieve something,
driven by ambitions.
We also left knowing that
the world had changed.
In 2016, when we were moving,
the borders were a lot more fluid.
Our biggest fear was that they could close
the borders and we wouldn't be able to return.
The beauty of the situation
is that we travel freely.
I could find myself in Moscow tomorrow,
meeting with someone, doing business.
The day after, I'll be in Singapore.
Then back here again.
That's great!
I've never encouraged anyone
to move away or run from something.
I get it that sometimes
you have to.
I've never done that.
I always moved TOWARDS.
If you believe that the place you're going to
has something that will help you achieve...
or just do something optimally,
dude, pack up and leave.
If you can't explain why you'll be more
efficient there than anywhere else,
you should think about it
and figure things out.
I believe it's much more important...
I think I told you this.
I believe it's much more important to live
for the things you were born for
rather than to live in the place
where you were born.
I think it's fine. The world's
gotten a lot smaller.
You can travel and move
at will.
If there's a place that lets you do what you
wanna do, you should pack up and go.
Without fear. Know that it's gonna be
tough but that you can persevere.
But moving just because this place is bad and
somewhere else will be better for some reason,
that's completely different.
I doubt it will... It seldom leads to
success and happiness.
When you...
When you HAVE TO leave,
you leave. I get it.
But the people that believe that the grass
is greener on the other side,
as a rule, eventually suffer
disappointment.
(title card music)
Here's how our attitude changed over
the course of these days in the Valley.
Initially, we were thinking:
what a strange world.
Then we realized that every
person you meet here
is either a startupper
or an investor.
Last night, I was already thinking
of investing into something.
(laughs) Caught the bug, huh?
Yeah. I have a certain amount
of money put aside.
Thought I'd store it away for a rainy day
or for the college fund or whatever.
- Now I'm looking for a startup to invest into.
- What for?
- Yeah.
- Well, first, this is interesting.
- Good.
I feel that this leads
to new knowledge.
If I invest into something, then obviously,
I'll get invested in the matter intellectually too.
And third, it's a backup plan.
You have good motivation.
Some people coming here say: "I have 50 mil
over here. Looking where to park 'em."
That's not a very good idea.
If your primary motivation is, "I wanna learn;
I wanna help create something big;
"I'm not afraid to lose money on this because
only 1 out of my 100 investments paid out,"
then you should start investing.
Though I never liked America.
I never thought I'd move to America.
I'd been to America many times,
obviously.
This place particularly,
on business.
But I never thought I'd live here.
But then I came here and felt like
I was at Yandex's campus.
Bunch of smiling faces with
excitement in their eyes.
People on hoverboards working
to change the future.
It felt a lot like Yandex' campus.
That's what I meant:
the Valley is the product
of a critical mass of people
creating a particular climate.
You're now in it, and it's
working its magic.
But it's exactly like the gold rush!
- Many are investing, admit it,
only to get rich.
- Yes.
And that's normal. That's capitalism.
But the difference between the gold rush
and what we're seeing today
is that gold you need to find
and then share.
Ideas you have to create,
and you can create them infinitely.
You know?
They multiply too.
One good idea yields two better ones,
and so on and so forth.
It's like a snowball effect.
That's the uniqueness of NOW.
It's not another gold rush.
It's not a zero-sum game,
where your gain is
someone else's loss.
It's a place where people co-create.
And the ecosystem of this
place only gets better.
For example, the iPhone allowed
YouTube to become better,
even though Google and Apple
are competitors.
Then Facebook, technically
a competitor to both of them,
further enhanced this ecosystem,
because it allowed you to share
YouTube links and so on.
Each company you build into this structure,
technically a competitor to everyone else,
in reality, they all enhance each other.
This place wasn't born 10, or 20,
or even 50 years ago.
150 years ago.
170. In 1849, when the gold
rush started here.
All of this is the fruit
of the gold rush.
It's the mentality of people striking dirt with
a pickaxe in hopes of finding a shit ton of gold.
- Same thing. They're perpetually consumed
by the gold rush here.
- So nothing changed?
When everyone was going crazy about
cryptocurrencies in Russia: "Bitcoin! Buy it!"
[*One of the largest Ponzi schemes in history]
[that operated in the 1990s.]
this was probably the first
Russian gold rush after MMM*.
- Yeah.
- No one even noticed it here.
Because something like this
happens here every 15 days.
Romania, Belarus, Indonesia, India, France —
they all tried to build a "Silicon Valley killer."
But that's impossible. At best, you can
build something of its own.
Because this place is a combination
of investment capital,
positive thinking,
Stanford and military research
that took place after WWII.
(Davidov) It emerged on its own around
Stanford and a few other local universities:
University of San Francisco, Berkeley
and Santa Clara University.
DARPA, basically an American defense
agency for strategic initiatives,
would give out grants to scientists
for all kinds of shit.
During the Vietnam War,
they researched telepathy,
trying to figure out if they could launch
psychokinetic attacks on people.
They funded that too.
They had this broad
investment program.
They also started funding local
university research labs
that gathered teams of people,
protected by American law,
who started developing things that
could potentially be commercialized.
People started investing
money into this stuff.
When it got big and started making money,
those initial investors became so rich
that people who heeded them
also started investing into this place.
State financing, military research,
development of IT and internet —
amalgamation of all these factors
led to the birth of the Valley.
You can't duplicate it. But you can
create something different.
Not even in Skolkovo?!
(laughs)
What's the best way to put it?
I can see that Russia is trying,
and we have some good companies.
Everyone knows Playrix,
Kaspersky, Yandex.
[Playrix is a mobile game developer founded in 2004]
[in Vologda by brothers Dmitriy and Igor Bouhman.]
[Combined monthly audience of Playrix's games]
[is over 100,000,000 users]
Everyone knows Playrix,
Kaspersky, Yandex.
[Playrix is a mobile game developer founded in 2004]
[in Vologda by brothers Dmitriy and Igor Bouhman.]
[Combined monthly audience of Playrix's games]
[is over 100,000,000 users]
Yandex makes drones,
some of the best in the world too.
[Playrix is a mobile game developer founded in 2004]
[in Vologda by brothers Dmitriy and Igor Bouhman.]
[Combined monthly audience of Playrix's games]
[is over 100,000,000 users]
We have our own way.
And it's great.
But no one's managed to copypaste
the Valley. And you don't need to.
You mean Skolkovo is a valid
part of our path too?
Out of the things I've seen
in Skolkovo,
I don't believe there was a single startup
that had succeeded globally.
On our way here, I stumbled upon
a video I hadn't seen before.
It was an NTV report about Dmitriy
Medvedev's visit to the Silicon Valley.
He says: "We'll open a Skolkovo
branch in the Valley."
Today, this sounds like a bad joke.
What's wrong with Skolkovo?
This is a tough and
complex question.
The groundwork was good.
Lots of typical Russian
problems got in the way.
One of them is corruption.
Another one is politics.
Third one is struggle over
resource control.
Which is basically a mix
of corruption and politics.
That's what happened in Skolkovo.
Has Skolkovo produced anything?
I don't believe so —
if we're talking about things other than their
business school, which is doing SOMETHING.
The Skolkovo technopark itself...
I've not seen anything good
over there.
Let me ask you as someone who wants
good things in Russia too:
why is the Valley possible
across the ocean,
but in our country,
somewhere in the Krasnodar Kray,
someplace near the sea,
or anywhere else,
in Skolkovo, I know how tasteless
mentioning it here is,
it's totally impossible?
You just answered it.
You started with a similar place.
When they build in Russia,
they first pick a place:
"Let's build a think tank!"
"Software engineers are like cockroaches!
We need to put a cardboard box on top of them."
"Then it's A-OK from there!"
In reality, you need to invest in the ecosystem,
in the sauce, in human interaction.
So what you're saying is,
creating something like this,
instead of copying geography,
you wanna build up
a place like Akademgorodok
in Novosibirsk.
[Akademgorodok is a research institute community]
[that gathered scientists from all over the USSR.]
[Founded in 1957 near Novosibirsk]
a place like Akademgorodok
in Novosibirsk.
[Akademgorodok is a research institute community]
[that gathered scientists from all over the USSR.]
[Founded in 1957 near Novosibirsk]
Yeah, exactly!
[Akademgorodok is a research institute community]
[that gathered scientists from all over the USSR.]
[Founded in 1957 near Novosibirsk]
Why aren't they doing it?
[Akademgorodok is a research institute community]
[that gathered scientists from all over the USSR.]
[Founded in 1957 near Novosibirsk]
Time. Networking and time.
You wanna switch things
around less.
Let people grow.
Keep them from dispersing.
'Cause a lot of the time, reaching certain
success, people pick up and leave.
You want an ecosystem
to gradually develop.
They should've started by putting
the interests of investors,
venture capitalists and angel
investors, on top.
Develop laws that would
save them the shaking.
- From the public bus joke?
- Yeah.
Our powers that be prioritize maintaining authority
over the interests of investors and the economy.
That's the main issue.
You mean the superior power?
Throughout. It permeates.
Why do you think no one makes any
investment deals under Russian law?
This FRII fund created by the Agency
for Strategic Initiatives,
only they make deals within
Russian jurisdiction.
Why is that?
Because no one believes that they could protect
their business interests under Russian law.
Even the smallest deals...
Scenario: I work as a sales
manager for some company.
I have $3000 of free capital.
My neighbor has a startup.
I wanna give him this money.
I'll be signing this deal
someplace like Cyprus.
I thought people did this
strictly because of taxes?
- No! Of course not!
- 'Cause you'd pay less taxes.
Not anymore. They introduced CFC.
You're not dodging shit.
Russia has small taxes.
Why try and dodge 13%?
It's 50% over here!
Depends on the tax.
Russian payroll tax is very high.
- Payroll tax is, yeah. But you're not gonna
process wages through Cyprus, are you?
- True.
You use offshore jurisdictions
specifically for investment deals.
Tax optimization costs zilch.
It's done specifically
for English law.
- Because our courts...
- So in case something happens you go to court
to the House of Representatives.
- Cyprus uses English law?
- Yes.
One of the reasons the Valley
emerged where it did
was, paradoxically, the fact that
this was lawless countryside.
West Coast was quite a bit
away from East Coast.
All the big companies
were on the East Coast.
They developed electric
lamps and stuff.
Well, the West Coast cowboys made them too,
nonchalantly ripping off East Coast technology.
Lucky for them, enforcing patent law
across the continent was a tall ask.
That's why venturous types
would come and stay here.
They formed a community
of peculiar personalities.
This community evolved
and evolved.
The Valley's all about networking.
That's why it works.
So the right way to do it wasn't building
a NEW think tank near Moscow,
but rather building up, again,
Akademgorodok or some such place
where smart people have been
living next to each other
and creating cool things
for decades?
Yeah. Especially when this new think tank
is super state-y and super official,
official and cool.
You get officials going,
"I want my son in there!"
"Now work! I'm paying
good money here!"
Maybe his son doesn't even want that,
but he'll go either way.
Instead you want mavericks.
- All breakthroughs are made by mavericks,
people who don't fit.
- By what now?
All breakthroughs are made
by mavericks.
Jobs was a maverick.
Gates is this four-eyed maverick.
- Revolutions are started by people
who don't fit normal life.
- Not by officials?
Yeah. People with normal lives don't
need revolutions. They're fine.
You wanna build around a university.
It's got academia.
Okay. But if a lousy soft science
graduate like myself gets it,
how come the guys ruling
the country didn't get it?
They did. They also knew that once they
picked an existing akademgorodok
or some other existing place,
struggle for resource control
would immediately ensue.
You can't start in MSU.
That would give the president
of MSU too much power.
And to Moscow. So it has to be
outside of Moscow.
You can't start in Novosibirsk
Akademgorodok,
because the region's governor
didn't do enough to deserve it.
It's politics.
Politics is stupid, and I try
to stay away from it.
It's not just Russia
that can't copy it.
At this stage, I think
no other place can.
For better or for worse, this is the place
where the right conditions coalesced.
Now this place attracts the kind of people
that can do all these things.
Sooner of later,
they end up here.
And...
If you took 10,000 of the most important
people here and moved them over to Russia,
that place would probably become
the new Silicon Valley.
But that's a tall ask,
'cause this place offers them an environment
that no other place can compete with.
'Cause people make the Valley.
It's not a place. It's not about
technoparks and pretty offices.
You could build pretty buildings in Dubai
or Skolkovo, or anywhere else
and dump a ton of money in it,
but if it doesn't have
this spirit of:
"We fail. We experiment."
"We're okay with doing
new crazy things,
"and no one's gonna look at us askance, on the contrary, it's encouraged,"
without those things, you can't
create another Valley.
They'll either produce derivative
and boring copies of things
or just ideas that aren't
innovative in any way.
You can't create something
like this artificially.
They emerge organically when
two kinds of people meet,
dreamers and people
with money.
And both have to feel
comfortable.
The two want different things.
Dreamers want set of conditions X;
people with money want Y.
- Fat cats and nerds?
- Fat cats and nerds. You could say that.
Nerds and investors.
This place has these things?
Yes, it does. Stanford and Berkeley...
It has several strong universities
with great academia.
They produce a constant flow of new...
nerds, as you called them.
At the same time, this is a nice and comfortable
enough place for people who've made billions.
So they don't leave to stay in their villas
in France and instead live here.
And this constant exchange where
some nerd could meet a billionaire
at some coffee place in Palo Alto
15 minutes away from their place,
they both live 15 minutes
away from it,
resulting in some sort of exchange of ideas
and subsequent investment contract,
that's what makes this
place so unique.
It's a tiny stretch of land.
You've driven around. 50 miles both ways.
That's the Valley. It's tiny.
This tiny stretch of land
generates a GDP
that's comparable to GDPs
of some countries.
Could something emerge in Russia
in the nearest future?
Nearest, no.
I can't see the light at the end
of the tunnel.
Maybe it's around the corner.
All we can do is look
to the future with hope.
Imagine that life is a playground.
Children come out to play.
Some play soccer, others play
pocketknife games.
You came out holding
a Junior Engineer set.
You like soldering radios.
That's your idea of fun as a kid.
You have time until sunset.
Mom's gonna call you soon:
"Andrew! Inside!"
I come out with my
Junior Engineer set.
I need a table.
Boys with the football
need a goal.
I need a table to sit there
and solder quietly.
I sit at a table, but it's occupied
by men.
They're not good or bad.
Just normal men.
They're cursing and playing
dominoes.
I sit next to them and try doing
the thing I came out for.
But they keep elbowing me and taking my
soldering iron away, stuff like that.
I have a few options.
I could give up and just go,
"Okay, I'm not gonna build this radio."
I could go, "Okay, I'll play
THEIR game."
I'll learn to play dominoes.
That's what they play at that table.
To hell with the radio.
I could start fighting
and locking horns.
That's yet another game. But it's not MY
Junior Engineer game.
Some do THAT.
But those older men...
They're older than me.
They've sat there longer than me.
The rules of their game were invented
long before any of us were around.
And there's another option:
pick up your set and find a table where
you can do what you wanted to do.
You'll build your radio. Might even treat
the dominoes crowd to some music.
That's basically what
happened with me.
I left,
(ending music starts playing quietly)
I did what I wanted
to do here,
but everyone's enjoying
the end result.
There's you. There's your channel.
There's Russian YouTube.
People are watching us
at this moment.
In part, thanks to my work.
(Dud') Do you think the older men
will ever scoot over?
(Doronichev) (sighs) I think they'll build
more tables. I hope so.
Those men need a place
too, you know?
Someone has to play
dominoes.
You can't change these
things by force.
I don't believe you can up and
re-build something in a jiffy.
You see? In this metaphor, sunset's coming.
Mom's gonna call you home soon.
I only have so many years in my life
to create something meaningful.
I can only create something
I'm good at.
That's why I'm merely choosing the environment
that lets me achieve this with maximum efficiency
and maximum benefit
for everybody.
(ending music)